<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<pc version="3">
    <character>
        <uniqueID>1146</uniqueID>
        <name>Carl Jr.</name>
        <imageData>
            <uniqueID>1149</uniqueID>
        </imageData>
        <race>
            <name>Gnome</name>
            <size>3</size>
            <speed>20</speed>
            <feat>
                <name>Ability Scores</name>
                <text>+2 Constitution, -2 Strength.</text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Low-Light Vision</name>
                <text>A gnome can see twice as far as a human in starlight, moonlight, torchlight, and similar
                    conditions of poor illumination. He retains the ability to distinguish color and detail under these
                    conditions.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Weapon Familiarity</name>
                <text>Gnomes may treat gnome hooked hammers as martial weapons rather than exotic weapons.</text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Illusion Resistance</name>
                <text>+2 racial bonus on saving throws against illusions.</text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Gnome Magic</name>
                <text>Add +1 to the Difficulty Class for all saving throws against illusion spells cast by gnomes. This
                    adjustment stacks with those from similar effects.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Hatred</name>
                <text>+1 racial bonus on attack rolls against kobolds and goblinoids.</text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Defensive Training</name>
                <text>+4 dodge bonus to Armor Class against monsters of the giant type. Any time a creature loses its
                    Dexterity bonus (if any) to Armor Class, such as when it’s caught flat-footed, it loses its dodge
                    bonus, too.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Keen Senses</name>
                <text>+2 racial bonus on Listen checks.</text>
                <modifier>
                    <category>2</category>
                    <type>28</type>
                    <value>2</value>
                </modifier>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Obsessive</name>
                <text>+2 racial bonus on Craft (alchemy) checks.</text>
                <modifier>
                    <category>2</category>
                    <type>5</type>
                    <value>2</value>
                </modifier>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Languages</name>
                <text>Common and Gnome. Bonus Languages: Draconic, Dwarven, Elven, Giant, Goblin, and Orc. In addition,
                    a gnome can speak with a burrowing mammal (a badger, fox, rabbit, or the like, see below). This
                    ability is innate to gnomes. See the speak with animals spell description.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Spell-Like Abilities</name>
                <text>1/day—speak with animals (burrowing mammal only, duration 1 minute). A gnome with a Charisma score
                    of at least 10 also has the following spell-like abilities: 1/day—dancing lights, ghost sound,
                    prestidigitation. Caster level 1st; save DC 10 + gnome’s Cha modifier + spell level.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Favored Class</name>
                <text>Bard. A multiclass gnome’s bard class does not count when determining whether he takes an
                    experience point penalty.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <modifier>
                <category>1</category>
                <type>2</type>
                <value>2</value>
            </modifier>
            <modifier>
                <category>1</category>
                <value>-2</value>
            </modifier>
            <modifier>
                <type>12</type>
                <value>1</value>
            </modifier>
        </race>
        <class>
            <id>1113</id>
            <name>Bard</name>
            <hd>1</hd>
            <skills>Appraise, Balance, Bluff, Climb, Concentration, Craft, Decipher Script, Diplomacy, Disguise, Escape
                Artist, Gather Information, Hide, Jump, Knowledge, Listen, Move Silently, Perform, Profession, Sense
                Motive, Sleight of Hand, Speak Language, Spellcraft, Swim, Tumble, Use Magic Device
            </skills>
            <skillPoints>6</skillPoints>
            <wealth>4d4x10</wealth>
            <reflex>2</reflex>
            <will>2</will>
            <slots>2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            <slotsCurrent>2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slotsCurrent>
            <feat>
                <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                <text>A bard is proficient with all simple weapons, plus the longsword, rapier, sap, short sword,
                    shortbow, and whip. Bards are proficient with light armor and shields (except tower shields). A bard
                    can cast bard spells while wearing light armor without incurring the normal arcane spell failure
                    chance. However, like any other arcane spellcaster, a bard wearing medium or heavy armor or using a
                    shield incurs a chance of arcane spell failure if the spell in question has a somatic component
                    (most do). A multiclass bard still incurs the normal arcane spell failure chance for arcane spells
                    received from other classes.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Spells</name>
                <text>A bard casts arcane spells, which are drawn from the bard spell list. He can cast any spell he
                    knows without preparing it ahead of time. Every bard spell has a verbal component (singing,
                    reciting, or music). To learn or cast a spell, a bard must have a Charisma score equal to at least
                    10 + the spell level. The Difficulty Class for a saving throw against a bard’s spell is 10 + the
                    spell level + the bard’s Charisma modifier.
                    Like other spellcasters, a bard can cast only a certain number of spells of each spell level per
                    day. His base daily spell allotment is given on Table: The Bard. In addition, he receives bonus
                    spells per day if he has a high Charisma score. When Table: The Bard indicates that the bard gets 0
                    spells per day of a given spell level, he gains only the bonus spells he would be entitled to based
                    on his Charisma score for that spell level.
                    The bard’s selection of spells is extremely limited. A bard begins play knowing four 0-level spells
                    of your choice. At most new bard levels, he gains one or more new spells, as indicated on Table: The
                    Bard. (Unlike spells per day, the number of spells a bard knows is not affected by his Charisma
                    score; the numbers on Table: The Bard are fixed.)
                    Upon reaching 5th level, and at every third bard level after that (8th, 11th, and so on), a bard can
                    choose to learn a new spell in place of one he already knows. In effect, the bard &#34;loses&#34;
                    the old spell in exchange for the new one. The new spell’s level must be the same as that of the
                    spell being exchanged, and it must be at least two levels lower than the highest-level bard spell
                    the bard can cast. A bard may swap only a single spell at any given level, and must choose whether
                    or not to swap the spell at the same time that he gains new spells known for the level.
                    As noted above, a bard need not prepare his spells in advance. He can cast any spell he knows at any
                    time, assuming he has not yet used up his allotment of spells per day for the spell’s level.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Bardic Knowledge</name>
                <text>A bard may make a special bardic knowledge check with a bonus equal to his bard level + his
                    Intelligence modifier to see whether he knows some relevant information about local notable people,
                    legendary items, or noteworthy places. (If the bard has 5 or more ranks in Knowledge (history), he
                    gains a +2 bonus on this check.)
                    A successful bardic knowledge check will not reveal the powers of a magic item but may give a hint
                    as to its general function. A bard may not take 10 or take 20 on this check; this sort of knowledge
                    is essentially random.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Bardic Music</name>
                <text>Once per day per bard level, a bard can use his song or poetics to produce magical effects on
                    those around him (usually including himself, if desired). While these abilities fall under the
                    category of bardic music and the descriptions discuss singing or playing instruments, they can all
                    be activated by reciting poetry, chanting, singing lyrical songs, singing melodies, whistling,
                    playing an instrument, or playing an instrument in combination with some spoken performance. Each
                    ability requires both a minimum bard level and a minimum number of ranks in the Perform skill to
                    qualify; if a bard does not have the required number of ranks in at least one Perform skill, he does
                    not gain the bardic music ability until he acquires the needed ranks.
                    Starting a bardic music effect is a standard action. Some bardic music abilities require
                    concentration, which means the bard must take a standard action each round to maintain the ability.
                    Even while using bardic music that doesn’t require concentration, a bard cannot cast spells,
                    activate magic items by spell completion (such as scrolls), spell trigger (such as wands), or
                    command word. Just as for casting a spell with a verbal component, a deaf bard has a 20% chance to
                    fail when attempting to use bardic music. If he fails, the attempt still counts against his daily
                    limit.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Countersong (Su)</name>
                <text>A bard with 3 or more ranks in a Perform skill can use his music or poetics to counter magical
                    effects that depend on sound (but not spells that simply have verbal components). Each round of the
                    countersong, he makes a Perform check. Any creature within 30 feet of the bard (including the bard
                    himself) that is affected by a sonic or language-dependent magical attack may use the bard’s Perform
                    check result in place of its saving throw if, after the saving throw is rolled, the Perform check
                    result proves to be higher. If a creature within range of the countersong is already under the
                    effect of a noninstantaneous sonic or language-dependent magical attack, it gains another saving
                    throw against the effect each round it hears the countersong, but it must use the bard’s Perform
                    check result for the save. Countersong has no effect against effects that don’t allow saves. The
                    bard may keep up the countersong for 10 rounds.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Fascinate (Sp)</name>
                <text>A bard with 3 or more ranks in a Perform skill can use his music or poetics to cause one or more
                    creatures to become fascinated with him. Each creature to be fascinated must be within 90 feet, able
                    to see and hear the bard, and able to pay attention to him. The bard must also be able to see the
                    creature. The distraction of a nearby combat or other dangers prevents the ability from working. For
                    every three levels a bard attains beyond 1st, he can target one additional creature with a single
                    use of this ability.
                    To use the ability, a bard makes a Perform check. His check result is the DC for each affected
                    creature’s Will save against the effect. If a creature’s saving throw succeeds, the bard cannot
                    attempt to fascinate that creature again for 24 hours. If its saving throw fails, the creature sits
                    quietly and listens to the song, taking no other actions, for as long as the bard continues to play
                    and concentrate (up to a maximum of 1 round per bard level). While fascinated, a target takes a -4
                    penalty on skill checks made as reactions, such as Listen and Spot checks. Any potential threat
                    requires the bard to make another Perform check and allows the creature a new saving throw against a
                    DC equal to the new Perform check result.
                    Any obvious threat, such as someone drawing a weapon, casting a spell, or aiming a ranged weapon at
                    the target, automatically breaks the effect. Fascinate is an enchantment (compulsion),
                    mind-affecting ability.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Inspire Courage (Su)</name>
                <text>A bard with 3 or more ranks in a Perform skill can use song or poetics to inspire courage in his
                    allies (including himself), bolstering them against fear and improving their combat abilities. To be
                    affected, an ally must be able to hear the bard sing. The effect lasts for as long as the ally hears
                    the bard sing and for 5 rounds thereafter. An affected ally receives a +1 morale bonus on saving
                    throws against charm and fear effects and a +1 morale bonus on attack and weapon damage rolls. At
                    8th level, and every six bard levels thereafter, this bonus increases by 1 (+2 at 8th, +3 at 14th,
                    and +4 at 20th). Inspire courage is a mind-affecting ability.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <autolevel>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>2</will>
                <slots>2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                    <text>A bard is proficient with all simple weapons, plus the longsword, rapier, sap, short sword,
                        shortbow, and whip. Bards are proficient with light armor and shields (except tower shields). A
                        bard can cast bard spells while wearing light armor without incurring the normal arcane spell
                        failure chance. However, like any other arcane spellcaster, a bard wearing medium or heavy armor
                        or using a shield incurs a chance of arcane spell failure if the spell in question has a somatic
                        component (most do). A multiclass bard still incurs the normal arcane spell failure chance for
                        arcane spells received from other classes.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Spells</name>
                    <text>A bard casts arcane spells, which are drawn from the bard spell list. He can cast any spell he
                        knows without preparing it ahead of time. Every bard spell has a verbal component (singing,
                        reciting, or music). To learn or cast a spell, a bard must have a Charisma score equal to at
                        least 10 + the spell level. The Difficulty Class for a saving throw against a bard’s spell is 10
                        + the spell level + the bard’s Charisma modifier.
                        Like other spellcasters, a bard can cast only a certain number of spells of each spell level per
                        day. His base daily spell allotment is given on Table: The Bard. In addition, he receives bonus
                        spells per day if he has a high Charisma score. When Table: The Bard indicates that the bard
                        gets 0 spells per day of a given spell level, he gains only the bonus spells he would be
                        entitled to based on his Charisma score for that spell level.
                        The bard’s selection of spells is extremely limited. A bard begins play knowing four 0-level
                        spells of your choice. At most new bard levels, he gains one or more new spells, as indicated on
                        Table: The Bard. (Unlike spells per day, the number of spells a bard knows is not affected by
                        his Charisma score; the numbers on Table: The Bard are fixed.)
                        Upon reaching 5th level, and at every third bard level after that (8th, 11th, and so on), a bard
                        can choose to learn a new spell in place of one he already knows. In effect, the bard &#34;loses&#34;
                        the old spell in exchange for the new one. The new spell’s level must be the same as that of the
                        spell being exchanged, and it must be at least two levels lower than the highest-level bard
                        spell the bard can cast. A bard may swap only a single spell at any given level, and must choose
                        whether or not to swap the spell at the same time that he gains new spells known for the level.
                        As noted above, a bard need not prepare his spells in advance. He can cast any spell he knows at
                        any time, assuming he has not yet used up his allotment of spells per day for the spell’s level.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bardic Knowledge</name>
                    <text>A bard may make a special bardic knowledge check with a bonus equal to his bard level + his
                        Intelligence modifier to see whether he knows some relevant information about local notable
                        people, legendary items, or noteworthy places. (If the bard has 5 or more ranks in Knowledge
                        (history), he gains a +2 bonus on this check.)
                        A successful bardic knowledge check will not reveal the powers of a magic item but may give a
                        hint as to its general function. A bard may not take 10 or take 20 on this check; this sort of
                        knowledge is essentially random.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bardic Music</name>
                    <text>Once per day per bard level, a bard can use his song or poetics to produce magical effects on
                        those around him (usually including himself, if desired). While these abilities fall under the
                        category of bardic music and the descriptions discuss singing or playing instruments, they can
                        all be activated by reciting poetry, chanting, singing lyrical songs, singing melodies,
                        whistling, playing an instrument, or playing an instrument in combination with some spoken
                        performance. Each ability requires both a minimum bard level and a minimum number of ranks in
                        the Perform skill to qualify; if a bard does not have the required number of ranks in at least
                        one Perform skill, he does not gain the bardic music ability until he acquires the needed ranks.
                        Starting a bardic music effect is a standard action. Some bardic music abilities require
                        concentration, which means the bard must take a standard action each round to maintain the
                        ability. Even while using bardic music that doesn’t require concentration, a bard cannot cast
                        spells, activate magic items by spell completion (such as scrolls), spell trigger (such as
                        wands), or command word. Just as for casting a spell with a verbal component, a deaf bard has a
                        20% chance to fail when attempting to use bardic music. If he fails, the attempt still counts
                        against his daily limit.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Countersong (Su)</name>
                    <text>A bard with 3 or more ranks in a Perform skill can use his music or poetics to counter magical
                        effects that depend on sound (but not spells that simply have verbal components). Each round of
                        the countersong, he makes a Perform check. Any creature within 30 feet of the bard (including
                        the bard himself) that is affected by a sonic or language-dependent magical attack may use the
                        bard’s Perform check result in place of its saving throw if, after the saving throw is rolled,
                        the Perform check result proves to be higher. If a creature within range of the countersong is
                        already under the effect of a noninstantaneous sonic or language-dependent magical attack, it
                        gains another saving throw against the effect each round it hears the countersong, but it must
                        use the bard’s Perform check result for the save. Countersong has no effect against effects that
                        don’t allow saves. The bard may keep up the countersong for 10 rounds.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Fascinate (Sp)</name>
                    <text>A bard with 3 or more ranks in a Perform skill can use his music or poetics to cause one or
                        more creatures to become fascinated with him. Each creature to be fascinated must be within 90
                        feet, able to see and hear the bard, and able to pay attention to him. The bard must also be
                        able to see the creature. The distraction of a nearby combat or other dangers prevents the
                        ability from working. For every three levels a bard attains beyond 1st, he can target one
                        additional creature with a single use of this ability.
                        To use the ability, a bard makes a Perform check. His check result is the DC for each affected
                        creature’s Will save against the effect. If a creature’s saving throw succeeds, the bard cannot
                        attempt to fascinate that creature again for 24 hours. If its saving throw fails, the creature
                        sits quietly and listens to the song, taking no other actions, for as long as the bard continues
                        to play and concentrate (up to a maximum of 1 round per bard level). While fascinated, a target
                        takes a -4 penalty on skill checks made as reactions, such as Listen and Spot checks. Any
                        potential threat requires the bard to make another Perform check and allows the creature a new
                        saving throw against a DC equal to the new Perform check result.
                        Any obvious threat, such as someone drawing a weapon, casting a spell, or aiming a ranged weapon
                        at the target, automatically breaks the effect. Fascinate is an enchantment (compulsion),
                        mind-affecting ability.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Inspire Courage (Su)</name>
                    <text>A bard with 3 or more ranks in a Perform skill can use song or poetics to inspire courage in
                        his allies (including himself), bolstering them against fear and improving their combat
                        abilities. To be affected, an ally must be able to hear the bard sing. The effect lasts for as
                        long as the ally hears the bard sing and for 5 rounds thereafter. An affected ally receives a +1
                        morale bonus on saving throws against charm and fear effects and a +1 morale bonus on attack and
                        weapon damage rolls. At 8th level, and every six bard levels thereafter, this bonus increases by
                        1 (+2 at 8th, +3 at 14th, and +4 at 20th). Inspire courage is a mind-affecting ability.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>2</level>
                <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>3,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>3</level>
                <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>3,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Inspire Competence (Su)</name>
                    <text>A bard of 3rd level or higher with 6 or more ranks in a Perform skill can use his music or
                        poetics to help an ally succeed at a task. The ally must be within 30 feet and able to see and
                        hear the bard. The bard must also be able to see the ally.
                        The ally gets a +2 competence bonus on skill checks with a particular skill as long as he or she
                        continues to hear the bard’s music. Certain uses of this ability are infeasible. The effect
                        lasts as long as the bard concentrates, up to a maximum of 2 minutes. A bard can’t inspire
                        competence in himself. Inspire competence is a mind-affecting ability.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>4</level>
                <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>4</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>3,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>5</level>
                <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>4</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>3,3,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>6</level>
                <baseAttack>4</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>5</reflex>
                <will>5</will>
                <slots>3,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Suggestion (Sp)</name>
                    <text>A bard of 6th level or higher with 9 or more ranks in a Perform skill can make a suggestion
                        (as the spell) to a creature that he has already fascinated. Using this ability does not break
                        the bard’s concentration on the fascinate effect, nor does it allow a second saving throw
                        against the fascinate effect.
                        Making a suggestion doesn’t count against a bard’s daily limit on bardic music performances. A
                        Will saving throw (DC 10 + ½ bard’s level + bard’s Cha modifier) negates the effect. This
                        ability affects only a single creature (but see mass suggestion, below). Suggestion is an
                        enchantment (compulsion), mind-affecting, language dependent ability.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>7</level>
                <baseAttack>5</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>5</reflex>
                <will>5</will>
                <slots>3,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>8</level>
                <baseAttack>6</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>6</reflex>
                <will>6</will>
                <slots>3,3,3,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>9</level>
                <baseAttack>6</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>6</reflex>
                <will>6</will>
                <slots>3,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Inspire Greatness (Su)</name>
                    <text>A bard of 9th level or higher with 12 or more ranks in a Perform skill can use music or
                        poetics to inspire greatness in himself or a single willing ally within 30 feet, granting him or
                        her extra fighting capability. For every three levels a bard attains beyond 9th, he can target
                        one additional ally with a single use of this ability (two at 12th level, three at 15th, four at
                        18th). To inspire greatness, a bard must sing and an ally must hear him sing. The effect lasts
                        for as long as the ally hears the bard sing and for 5 rounds thereafter. A creature inspired
                        with greatness gains 2 bonus Hit Dice (d10s), the commensurate number of temporary hit points
                        (apply the target’s Constitution modifier, if any, to these bonus Hit Dice), a +2 competence
                        bonus on attack rolls, and a +1 competence bonus on Fortitude saves. The bonus Hit Dice count as
                        regular Hit Dice for determining the effect of spells that are Hit Dice dependant. Inspire
                        greatness is a mind-affecting ability.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>10</level>
                <baseAttack>7</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>7</reflex>
                <will>7</will>
                <slots>3,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>11</level>
                <baseAttack>8</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>7</reflex>
                <will>7</will>
                <slots>3,3,3,3,1,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>12</level>
                <baseAttack>9</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>8</reflex>
                <will>8</will>
                <slots>3,3,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Song of Freedom (Sp)</name>
                    <text>A bard of 12th level or higher with 15 or more ranks in a Perform skill can use music or
                        poetics to create an effect equivalent to the break enchantment spell (caster level equals the
                        character’s bard level). Using this ability requires 1 minute of uninterrupted concentration and
                        music, and it functions on a single target within 30 feet. A bard can’t use song of freedom on
                        himself.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>13</level>
                <baseAttack>9</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>8</reflex>
                <will>8</will>
                <slots>3,3,0,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>14</level>
                <baseAttack>10</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>9</reflex>
                <will>9</will>
                <slots>4,3,3,3,3,1,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>15</level>
                <baseAttack>11</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>9</reflex>
                <will>9</will>
                <slots>4,4,3,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Inspire Heroics (Su)</name>
                    <text>A bard of 15th level or higher with 18 or more ranks in a Perform skill can use music or
                        poetics to inspire tremendous heroism in himself or a single willing ally within 30 feet. For
                        every three bard levels the character attains beyond 15th, he can inspire heroics in one
                        additional creature. To inspire heroics, a bard must sing and an ally must hear the bard sing
                        for a full round. A creature so inspired gains a +4 morale bonus on saving throws and a +4 dodge
                        bonus to AC. The effect lasts for as long as the ally hears the bard sing and for up to 5 rounds
                        thereafter. Inspire heroics is a mind-affecting ability.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>16</level>
                <baseAttack>12</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>10</reflex>
                <will>10</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>17</level>
                <baseAttack>12</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>10</reflex>
                <will>10</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,3,3,1,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>18</level>
                <baseAttack>13</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>11</reflex>
                <will>11</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,3,2,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Mass Suggestion (Sp)</name>
                    <text>This ability functions like suggestion, above, except that a bard of 18th level or higher with
                        21 or more ranks in a Perform skill can make the suggestion simultaneously to any number of
                        creatures that he has already fascinated. Mass suggestion is an enchantment (compulsion),
                        mind-affecting, language-dependent ability.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>19</level>
                <baseAttack>14</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>11</reflex>
                <will>11</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,3,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>20</level>
                <baseAttack>15</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>12</reflex>
                <will>12</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,4,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <skills>Appraise, Balance, Bluff, Climb, Concentration, Craft, Decipher Script, Diplomacy, Disguise, Escape
                Artist, Gather Information, Hide, Jump, Knowledge, Listen, Move Silently, Perform, Profession, Sense
                Motive, Sleight of Hand, Speak Language, Spellcraft, Swim, Tumble, Use Magic Device
            </skills>
            <spellAbility>6</spellAbility>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Mage Hand</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One nonmagical, unattended object weighing up to 5 lb.</target>
                <duration>Concentration</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You point your finger at an object and can lift it and move it at will from a distance. As a move
                    action, you can propel the object as far as 15 feet in any direction, though the spell ends if the
                    distance between you and the object ever exceeds the spell’s range.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Mending</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>10 ft.</range>
                <target>One object of up to 1 lb.</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless, object)</save>
                <sr>Yes (harmless, object)</sr>
                <text>Mending repairs small breaks or tears in objects (but not warps, such as might be caused by a warp
                    wood spell). It will weld broken metallic objects such as a ring, a chain link, a medallion, or a
                    slender dagger, providing but one break exists.
                    Ceramic or wooden objects with multiple breaks can be invisibly rejoined to be as strong as new. A
                    hole in a leather sack or a wineskin is completely healed over by mending. The spell can repair a
                    magic item, but the item’s magical abilities are not restored. The spell cannot mend broken magic
                    rods, staffs, or wands, nor does it affect creatures (including constructs).
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Detect Magic</name>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>60 ft.</range>
                <area>Cone-shaped emanation</area>
                <duration>Concentration, up to 1 min./level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You detect magical auras. The amount of information revealed depends on how long you study a
                    particular area or subject.
                    1st Round: Presence or absence of magical auras.
                    2nd Round: Number of different magical auras and the power of the most potent aura.
                    3rd Round: The strength and location of each aura. If the items or creatures bearing the auras are
                    in line of sight, you can make Spellcraft skill checks to determine the school of magic involved in
                    each. (Make one check per aura; DC 15 + spell level, or 15 + half caster level for a nonspell
                    effect.)
                    Magical areas, multiple types of magic, or strong local magical emanations may distort or conceal
                    weaker auras.
                    Aura Strength: An aura’s power depends on a spell’s functioning spell level or an item’s caster
                    level. If an aura falls into more than one category, detect magic indicates the stronger of the two.
                    Lingering Aura: A magical aura lingers after its original source dissipates (in the case of a spell)
                    or is destroyed (in the case of a magic item). If detect magic is cast and directed at such a
                    location, the spell indicates an aura strength of dim (even weaker than a faint aura). How long the
                    aura lingers at this dim level depends on its original power:
                    Outsiders and elementals are not magical in themselves, but if they are summoned, the conjuration
                    spell registers.
                    Each round, you can turn to detect magic in a new area. The spell can penetrate barriers, but 1 foot
                    of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead, or 3 feet of wood or dirt blocks it.
                    Detect magic can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Message</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <target>One creature/level</target>
                <duration>10 min./level</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You can whisper messages and receive whispered replies with little chance of being overheard. You
                    point your finger at each creature you want to receive the message. When you whisper, the whispered
                    message is audible to all targeted creatures within range. Magical silence, 1 foot of stone, 1 inch
                    of common metal (or a thin sheet of lead), or 3 feet of wood or dirt blocks the spell. The message
                    does not have to travel in a straight line. It can circumvent a barrier if there is an open path
                    between you and the subject, and the path’s entire length lies within the spell’s range. The
                    creatures that receive the message can whisper a reply that you hear. The spell transmits sound, not
                    meaning. It doesn’t transcend language barriers.
                    Note: To speak a message, you must mouth the words and whisper, possibly allowing observers the
                    opportunity to read your lips.
                    Focus: A short piece of copper wire.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
        </class>
        <class>
            <id>1098</id>
            <name>Wizard</name>
            <level>6</level>
            <hd>0</hd>
            <skills>Concentration, Craft, Decipher Script, Knowledge, Profession, Spellcraft</skills>
            <wealth>3d4x10</wealth>
            <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
            <fortitude>2</fortitude>
            <reflex>2</reflex>
            <will>5</will>
            <slots>4,4,3,2,1,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            <slotsCurrent>4,3,2,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slotsCurrent>
            <feat>
                <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                <text>Wizards are proficient with the club, dagger, heavy crossbow, light crossbow, and quarterstaff,
                    but not with any type of armor or shield. Armor of any type interferes with a wizard’s movements,
                    which can cause her spells with somatic components to fail.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Spells</name>
                <text>A wizard casts arcane spells which are drawn from the sorcerer/wizard spell list. A wizard must
                    choose and prepare her spells ahead of time (see below).
                    To learn, prepare, or cast a spell, the wizard must have an Intelligence score equal to at least 10
                    + the spell level. The Difficulty Class for a saving throw against a wizard’s spell is 10 + the
                    spell level + the wizard’s Intelligence modifier.
                    Like other spellcasters, a wizard can cast only a certain number of spells of each spell level per
                    day. Her base daily spell allotment is given on Table: The Wizard. In addition, she receives bonus
                    spells per day if she has a high Intelligence score.
                    Unlike a bard or sorcerer, a wizard may know any number of spells. She must choose and prepare her
                    spells ahead of time by getting a good night’s sleep and spending 1 hour studying her spellbook.
                    While studying, the wizard decides which spells to prepare.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Spellbooks</name>
                <text>A wizard must study her spellbook each day to prepare her spells. She cannot prepare any spell not
                    recorded in her spellbook, except for read magic, which all wizards can prepare from memory.
                    A wizard begins play with a spellbook containing all 0-level wizard spells (except those from her
                    prohibited school or schools, if any; see School Specialization, below) plus three 1st-level spells
                    of your choice. For each point of Intelligence bonus the wizard has, the spellbook holds one
                    additional 1st-level spell of your choice. At each new wizard level, she gains two new spells of any
                    spell level or levels that she can cast (based on her new wizard level) for her spellbook. At any
                    time, a wizard can also add spells found in other wizards’ spellbooks to her own.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Bonus Languages</name>
                <text>A wizard may substitute Draconic for one of the bonus languages available to the character because
                    of her race.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Familiar</name>
                <text>A wizard can obtain a familiar in exactly the same manner as a sorcerer can.</text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Scribe Scroll</name>
                <text>At 1st level, a wizard gains Scribe Scroll as a bonus feat.</text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Bonus Feats</name>
                <text>At 5th level, a wizard gains a bonus feat. At each such opportunity, she can choose a metamagic
                    feat, an item creation feat, or Spell Mastery. The wizard must still meet all prerequisites for a
                    bonus feat, including caster level minimums.
                    These bonus feats are in addition to the feat that a character of any class gets from advancing
                    levels. The wizard is not limited to the categories of item creation feats, metamagic feats, or
                    Spell Mastery when choosing these feats.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <autolevel>
                <will>2</will>
                <slots>3,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                    <text>Wizards are proficient with the club, dagger, heavy crossbow, light crossbow, and
                        quarterstaff, but not with any type of armor or shield. Armor of any type interferes with a
                        wizard’s movements, which can cause her spells with somatic components to fail.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Spells</name>
                    <text>A wizard casts arcane spells which are drawn from the sorcerer/wizard spell list. A wizard
                        must choose and prepare her spells ahead of time (see below).
                        To learn, prepare, or cast a spell, the wizard must have an Intelligence score equal to at least
                        10 + the spell level. The Difficulty Class for a saving throw against a wizard’s spell is 10 +
                        the spell level + the wizard’s Intelligence modifier.
                        Like other spellcasters, a wizard can cast only a certain number of spells of each spell level
                        per day. Her base daily spell allotment is given on Table: The Wizard. In addition, she receives
                        bonus spells per day if she has a high Intelligence score.
                        Unlike a bard or sorcerer, a wizard may know any number of spells. She must choose and prepare
                        her spells ahead of time by getting a good night’s sleep and spending 1 hour studying her
                        spellbook. While studying, the wizard decides which spells to prepare.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Spellbooks</name>
                    <text>A wizard must study her spellbook each day to prepare her spells. She cannot prepare any spell
                        not recorded in her spellbook, except for read magic, which all wizards can prepare from memory.
                        A wizard begins play with a spellbook containing all 0-level wizard spells (except those from
                        her prohibited school or schools, if any; see School Specialization, below) plus three 1st-level
                        spells of your choice. For each point of Intelligence bonus the wizard has, the spellbook holds
                        one additional 1st-level spell of your choice. At each new wizard level, she gains two new
                        spells of any spell level or levels that she can cast (based on her new wizard level) for her
                        spellbook. At any time, a wizard can also add spells found in other wizards’ spellbooks to her
                        own.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Languages</name>
                    <text>A wizard may substitute Draconic for one of the bonus languages available to the character
                        because of her race.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Familiar</name>
                    <text>A wizard can obtain a familiar in exactly the same manner as a sorcerer can.</text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Scribe Scroll</name>
                    <text>At 1st level, a wizard gains Scribe Scroll as a bonus feat.</text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>2</level>
                <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>4,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>3</level>
                <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>4,2,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>4</level>
                <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>4,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>5</level>
                <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>4,3,2,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Feats</name>
                    <text>At 5th level, a wizard gains a bonus feat. At each such opportunity, she can choose a
                        metamagic feat, an item creation feat, or Spell Mastery. The wizard must still meet all
                        prerequisites for a bonus feat, including caster level minimums.
                        These bonus feats are in addition to the feat that a character of any class gets from advancing
                        levels. The wizard is not limited to the categories of item creation feats, metamagic feats, or
                        Spell Mastery when choosing these feats.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>6</level>
                <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>5</will>
                <slots>4,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>7</level>
                <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>5</will>
                <slots>4,4,3,2,1,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>8</level>
                <baseAttack>4</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>6</will>
                <slots>4,4,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>9</level>
                <baseAttack>4</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>6</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,3,2,1,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>10</level>
                <baseAttack>5</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>7</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Feats</name>
                    <text>At 10th, a wizard gains a bonus feat. At each such opportunity, she can choose a metamagic
                        feat, an item creation feat, or Spell Mastery. The wizard must still meet all prerequisites for
                        a bonus feat, including caster level minimums.
                        These bonus feats are in addition to the feat that a character of any class gets from advancing
                        levels. The wizard is not limited to the categories of item creation feats, metamagic feats, or
                        Spell Mastery when choosing these feats.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>11</level>
                <baseAttack>5</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>7</will>
                <slots>4,6,4,4,3,2,1,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>12</level>
                <baseAttack>6</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>4</reflex>
                <will>8</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,3,3,2,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>13</level>
                <baseAttack>6</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>4</reflex>
                <will>8</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,3,2,1,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>14</level>
                <baseAttack>7</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>4</reflex>
                <will>9</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,3,3,2,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>15</level>
                <baseAttack>7</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>5</reflex>
                <will>9</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,3,2,1,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Feats</name>
                    <text>At 15th, a wizard gains a bonus feat. At each such opportunity, she can choose a metamagic
                        feat, an item creation feat, or Spell Mastery. The wizard must still meet all prerequisites for
                        a bonus feat, including caster level minimums.
                        These bonus feats are in addition to the feat that a character of any class gets from advancing
                        levels. The wizard is not limited to the categories of item creation feats, metamagic feats, or
                        Spell Mastery when choosing these feats.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>16</level>
                <baseAttack>8</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>5</reflex>
                <will>10</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,3,3,2,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>17</level>
                <baseAttack>8</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>5</reflex>
                <will>10</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,4,3,2,1,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>18</level>
                <baseAttack>9</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>6</reflex>
                <will>11</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,4,3,3,2,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>19</level>
                <baseAttack>9</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>6</reflex>
                <will>11</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,4,4,3,3,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>20</level>
                <baseAttack>10</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>6</reflex>
                <will>12</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,4,4,4,4,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Feats</name>
                    <text>At 20th level, a wizard gains a bonus feat. At each such opportunity, she can choose a
                        metamagic feat, an item creation feat, or Spell Mastery. The wizard must still meet all
                        prerequisites for a bonus feat, including caster level minimums.
                        These bonus feats are in addition to the feat that a character of any class gets from advancing
                        levels. The wizard is not limited to the categories of item creation feats, metamagic feats, or
                        Spell Mastery when choosing these feats.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <skills>Concentration, Craft, Decipher Script, Knowledge, Profession, Spellcraft</skills>
            <spellAbility>4</spellAbility>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Glitterdust</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <area>Creatures and objects within 10-ft.-radius spread</area>
                <duration>1 round/level</duration>
                <save>Will negates (blinding only)</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>A cloud of golden particles covers everyone and everything in the area, causing creatures to
                    become blinded and visibly outlining invisible things for the duration of the spell. All within the
                    area are covered by the dust, which cannot be removed and continues to sparkle until it fades.
                    Any creature covered by the dust takes a –40 penalty on Hide checks.
                    Material Component: Ground mica.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Summon Monster I</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, F/DF</components>
                <time>1 round</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>One summoned creature</effect>
                <duration>1 round/level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell summons an extraplanar creature (typically an outsider, elemental, or magical beast
                    native to another plane). It appears where you designate and acts immediately, on your turn. It
                    attacks your opponents to the best of its ability. If you can communicate with the creature, you can
                    direct it not to attack, to attack particular enemies, or to perform other actions.
                    The spell conjures one of the creatures from the 1st-level list on the accompanying Summon Monster
                    table. You choose which kind of creature to summon, and you can change that choice each time you
                    cast the spell.
                    A summoned monster cannot summon or otherwise conjure another creature, nor can it use any
                    teleportation or planar travel abilities. Creatures cannot be summoned into an environment that
                    cannot support them.
                    When you use a summoning spell to summon an air, chaotic, earth, evil, fire, good, lawful, or water
                    creature, it is a spell of that type.
                    Arcane Focus: A tiny bag and a small (not necessarily lit) candle.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Read Magic</name>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, S, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Personal</range>
                <target>You</target>
                <duration>10 min./level</duration>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>By means of read magic, you can decipher magical inscriptions on objects—books, scrolls, weapons,
                    and the like—that would otherwise be unintelligible. This deciphering does not normally invoke the
                    magic contained in the writing, although it may do so in the case of a cursed scroll. Furthermore,
                    once the spell is cast and you have read the magical inscription, you are thereafter able to read
                    that particular writing without recourse to the use of read magic. You can read at the rate of one
                    page (250 words) per minute. The spell allows you to identify a glyph of warding with a DC 13
                    Spellcraft check, a greater glyph of warding with a DC 16 Spellcraft check, or any symbol spell with
                    a Spellcraft check (DC 10 + spell level).
                    Read magic can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                    Focus: A clear crystal or mineral prism.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Paladin</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Ranger</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Magic Missile</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <target>Up to five creatures, no two of which can be more than 15 ft. apart</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>A missile of magical energy darts forth from your fingertip and strikes its target, dealing 1d4+1
                    points of force damage.
                    The missile strikes unerringly, even if the target is in melee combat or has less than total cover
                    or total concealment. Specific parts of a creature can’t be singled out. Inanimate objects are not
                    damaged by the spell.
                    For every two caster levels beyond 1st, you gain an additional missile—two at 3rd level, three at
                    5th, four at 7th, and the maximum of five missiles at 9th level or higher. If you shoot multiple
                    missiles, you can have them strike a single creature or several creatures. A single missile can
                    strike only one creature. You must designate targets before you check for spell resistance or roll
                    damage.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>4</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Black Tentacles</name>
                <level>4</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <area>20-ft.-radius spread</area>
                <duration>1 round/level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell conjures a field of rubbery black tentacles, each 10 feet long. These waving members
                    seem to spring forth from the earth, floor, or whatever surface is underfoot—including water. They
                    grasp and entwine around creatures that enter the area, holding them fast and crushing them with
                    great strength.
                    Every creature within the area of the spell must make a grapple check, opposed by the grapple check
                    of the tentacles. Treat the tentacles attacking a particular target as a Large creature with a base
                    attack bonus equal to your caster level and a Strength score of 19. Thus, its grapple check modifier
                    is equal to your caster level +8. The tentacles are immune to all types of damage.
                    Once the tentacles grapple an opponent, they may make a grapple check each round on your turn to
                    deal 1d6+4 points of bludgeoning damage. The tentacles continue to crush the opponent until the
                    spell ends or the opponent escapes.
                    Any creature that enters the area of the spell is immediately attacked by the tentacles. Even
                    creatures who aren’t grappling with the tentacles may move through the area at only half normal
                    speed.
                    Material Component: A piece of tentacle from a giant octopus or a giant squid.

                    Clarifications: no touch attack by forum consensus and raw. Only one grapple attempt per target by
                    faq.


                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Cone of Cold</name>
                <level>5</level>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S, M/DF</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>60 ft.</range>
                <area>Cone-shaped burst</area>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Reflex half</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>Cone of cold creates an area of extreme cold, originating at your hand and extending outward in a
                    cone. It drains heat, dealing 1d6 points of cold damage per caster level (maximum 15d6).
                    Arcane Material Component: A very small crystal or glass cone.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>5</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>5</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>6</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <name>Change Self</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>6</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</time>
                <range>60 feet</range>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <sr>No</sr>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Summon Monster II</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, F/DF</components>
                <time>1 round</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>One or more summoned creatures, no two of which can be more than 30 ft. apart</effect>
                <duration>1 round/level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell functions like summon monster I, except that you can summon one creature from the
                    2nd-level list or 1d3 creatures of the same kind from the 1st-level list.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Mage Hand</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One nonmagical, unattended object weighing up to 5 lb.</target>
                <duration>Concentration</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You point your finger at an object and can lift it and move it at will from a distance. As a move
                    action, you can propel the object as far as 15 feet in any direction, though the spell ends if the
                    distance between you and the object ever exceeds the spell’s range.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Obscuring Mist</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>20 ft.</range>
                <effect>Cloud spreads in 20-ft. radius from you, 20 ft. high</effect>
                <duration>1 min./level</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>A misty vapor arises around you. It is stationary once created. The vapor obscures all sight,
                    including darkvision, beyond 5 feet. A creature 5 feet away has concealment (attacks have a 20% miss
                    chance). Creatures farther away have total concealment (50% miss chance, and the attacker cannot use
                    sight to locate the target).
                    A moderate wind (11+ mph), such as from a gust of wind spell, disperses the fog in 4 rounds. A
                    strong wind (21+ mph) disperses the fog in 1 round. A fireball, flame strike, or similar spell burns
                    away the fog in the explosive or fiery spell’s area. A wall of fire burns away the fog in the area
                    into which it deals damage.
                    This spell does not function underwater.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Prestidigitation</name>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>10 ft.</range>
                <target>See text</target>
                <duration>1 hour</duration>
                <save>See text</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Prestidigitations are minor tricks that novice spellcasters use for practice. Once cast, a
                    prestidigitation spell enables you to perform simple magical effects for 1 hour. The effects are
                    minor and have severe limitations. A prestidigitation can slowly lift 1 pound of material. It can
                    color, clean, or soil items in a 1-foot cube each round. It can chill, warm, or flavor 1 pound of
                    nonliving material. It cannot deal damage or affect the concentration of spellcasters.
                    Prestidigitation can create small objects, but they look crude and artificial. The materials created
                    by a prestidigitation spell are extremely fragile, and they cannot be used as tools, weapons, or
                    spell components. Finally, a prestidigitation lacks the power to duplicate any other spell effects.
                    Any actual change to an object (beyond just moving, cleaning, or soiling it) persists only 1 hour.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Protection from Arrows</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>1</school>
                <components>V, S, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Creature touched</target>
                <duration>1 hour/level or until discharged</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless)</save>
                <sr>Yes (harmless)</sr>
                <text>The warded creature gains resistance to ranged weapons. The subject gains damage reduction
                    10/magic against ranged weapons. (This spell doesn’t grant you the ability to damage creatures with
                    similar damage reduction.) Once the spell has prevented a total of 10 points of damage per caster
                    level (maximum 100 points), it is discharged.
                    Focus: A piece of shell from a tortoise or a turtle.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Teleport</name>
                <level>5</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Personal and touch</range>
                <target>You appear safely a random distance away from the destination in a random direction. Distance
                    off target is 1d10x1d10% of the distance that was to be traveled. The direction off target is
                    determined randomly
                </target>
                <area>You wind up in an area that’s visually or thematically similar to the target area.</area>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None and Will negates (object)</save>
                <sr>No and Yes (object)</sr>
                <text>This spell instantly transports you to a designated destination, which may be as distant as 100
                    miles per caster level. Interplanar travel is not possible. You can bring along objects as long as
                    their weight doesn’t exceed your maximum load. You may also bring one additional willing Medium or
                    smaller creature (carrying gear or objects up to its maximum load) or its equivalent (see below) per
                    three caster levels. A Large creature counts as two Medium creatures, a Huge creature counts as two
                    Large creatures, and so forth. All creatures to be transported must be in contact with one another,
                    and at least one of those creatures must be in contact with you. As with all spells where the range
                    is personal and the target is you, you need not make a saving throw, nor is spell resistance
                    applicable to you. Only objects held or in use (attended) by another person receive saving throws
                    and spell resistance.
                    You must have some clear idea of the location and layout of the destination. The clearer your mental
                    image, the more likely the teleportation works. Areas of strong physical or magical energy may make
                    teleportation more hazardous or even impossible.
                    To see how well the teleportation works, roll d% and consult the Teleport table. Refer to the
                    following information for definitions of the terms on the table.
                    Familiarity: “Very familiar” is a place where you have been very often and where you feel at home.
                    “Studied carefully” is a place you know well, either because you can currently see it, you’ve been
                    there often, or you have used other means (such as scrying) to study the place for at least one
                    hour. “Seen casually” is a place that you have seen more than once but with which you are not very
                    familiar. “Viewed once” is a place that you have seen once, possibly using magic.
                    “False destination” is a place that does not truly exist or if you are teleporting to an otherwise
                    familiar location that no longer exists as such or has been so completely altered as to no longer be
                    familiar to you. When traveling to a false destination, roll 1d20+80 to obtain results on the table,
                    rather than rolling d%, since there is no real destination for you to hope to arrive at or even be
                    off target from.
                    You appear where you want to be.
                    You appear safely a random distance away from the destination in a random direction. Distance off
                    target is 1d10x1d10% of the distance that was to be traveled. The direction off target is determined
                    randomly
                    You wind up in an area that’s visually or thematically similar to the target area.
                    Generally, you appear in the closest similar place within range. If no such area exists within the
                    spell’s range, the spell simply fails instead.
                    Mishap: You and anyone else teleporting with you have gotten “scrambled.” You each take 1d10 points
                    of damage, and you reroll on the chart to see where you wind up. For these rerolls, roll 1d20+80.
                    Each time “Mishap” comes up, the characters take more damage and must reroll.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>5</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>5</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>5</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Open/Close</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>Object weighing up to 30 lb. or portal that can be opened or closed</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Will negates (object)</save>
                <sr>Yes (object)</sr>
                <text>You can open or close (your choice) a door, chest, box, window, bag, pouch, bottle, barrel, or
                    other container. If anything resists this activity (such as a bar on a door or a lock on a chest),
                    the spell fails. In addition, the spell can only open and close things weighing 30 pounds or less.
                    Thus, doors, chests, and similar objects sized for enormous creatures may be beyond this spell’s
                    ability to affect.
                    Focus: A brass key.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Dancing Lights</name>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <effect>Up to four lights, all within a 10- ft.-radius area</effect>
                <duration>1 minute (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Depending on the version selected, you create up to four lights that resemble lanterns or torches
                    (and cast that amount of light), or up to four glowing spheres of light (which look like
                    will-o’-wisps), or one faintly glowing, vaguely humanoid shape. The dancing lights must stay within
                    a 10-foot-radius area in relation to each other but otherwise move as you desire (no concentration
                    required): forward or back, up or down, straight or turning corners, or the like. The lights can
                    move up to 100 feet per round. A light winks out if the distance between you and it exceeds the
                    spell’s range.
                    Dancing lights can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Acid Splash</name>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>One missile of acid</effect>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You fire a small orb of acid at the target. You must succeed on a ranged touch attack to hit your
                    target. The orb deals 1d3 points of acid damage.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Shadow Conjuration</name>
                <level>4</level>
                <school>6</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>See text</range>
                <effect>See text</effect>
                <duration>See text</duration>
                <save>Will disbelief (if interacted with); varies; see text</save>
                <sr>Yes; see text</sr>
                <text>You use material from the Plane of Shadow to shape quasi-real illusions of one or more creatures,
                    objects, or forces. Shadow conjuration can mimic any sorcerer or wizard conjuration (summoning) or
                    conjuration (creation) spell of 3rd level or lower.
                    Shadow conjurations are actually one-fifth (20%) as strong as the real things, though creatures who
                    believe the shadow conjurations to be real are affected by them at full strength.
                    Any creature that interacts with the conjured object, force, or creature can make a Will save to
                    recognize its true nature.
                    Spells that deal damage have normal effects unless the affected creature succeeds on a Will save.
                    Each disbelieving creature takes only one-fifth (20%) damage from the attack. If the disbelieved
                    attack has a special effect other than damage, that effect is only 20% likely to occur. Regardless
                    of the result of the save to disbelieve, an affected creature is also allowed any save that the
                    spell being simulated allows, but the save DC is set according to shadow conjuration’s level (4th)
                    rather than the spell’s normal level. In addition, any effect created by shadow conjuration allows
                    spell resistance, even if the spell it is simulating does not. Shadow objects or substances have
                    normal effects except against those who disbelieve them.
                    Against disbelievers, they are 20% likely to work.
                    A shadow creature has one-fifth the hit points of a normal creature of its kind (regardless of
                    whether it’s recognized as shadowy). It deals normal damage and has all normal abilities and
                    weaknesses. Against a creature that recognizes it as a shadow creature, however, the shadow
                    creature’s damage is one-fifth (20%) normal, and all special abilities that do not deal lethal
                    damage are only 20% likely to work. (Roll for each use and each affected character separately.)
                    Furthermore, the shadow creature’s AC bonuses are one-fifth as large.
                    A creature that succeeds on its save sees the shadow conjurations as transparent images superimposed
                    on vague, shadowy forms.
                    Objects automatically succeed on their Will saves against this spell.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Light</name>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, M/DF</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Object touched</target>
                <duration>10 min./level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell causes an object to glow like a torch, shedding bright light in a 20-foot radius (and
                    dim light for an additional 20 feet) from the point you touch. The effect is immobile, but it can be
                    cast on a movable object. Light taken into an area of magical darkness does not function.
                    A light spell (one with the light descriptor) counters and dispels a darkness spell (one with the
                    darkness descriptor) of an equal or lower level.
                    Arcane Material Component: A firefly or a piece of phosphorescent moss.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Unseen Servant</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>One invisible, mindless, shapeless servant</effect>
                <duration>1 hour/level</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>An unseen servant is an invisible, mindless, shapeless force that performs simple tasks at your
                    command. It can run and fetch things, open unstuck doors, and hold chairs, as well as clean and
                    mend. The servant can perform only one activity at a time, but it repeats the same activity over and
                    over again if told to do so as long as you remain within range. It can open only normal doors,
                    drawers, lids, and the like. It has an effective Strength score of 2 (so it can lift 20 pounds or
                    drag 100 pounds). It can trigger traps and such, but it can exert only 20 pounds of force, which is
                    not enough to activate certain pressure plates and other devices. It can’t perform any task that
                    requires a skill check with a DC higher than 10 or that requires a check using a skill that can’t be
                    used untrained. Its speed is 15 feet.
                    The servant cannot attack in any way; it is never allowed an attack roll. It cannot be killed, but
                    it dissipates if it takes 6 points of damage from area attacks. (It gets no saves against attacks.)
                    If you attempt to send it beyond the spell’s range (measured from your current position), the
                    servant ceases to exist.
                    Material Component: A piece of string and a bit of wood.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Grease</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One object or a 10-ft. square</target>
                <duration>1 round/level (D)</duration>
                <save>See text</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>A grease spell covers a solid surface with a layer of slippery grease. Any creature in the area
                    when the spell is cast must make a successful Reflex save or fall. This save is repeated on your
                    turn each round that the creature remains within the area. A creature can walk within or through the
                    area of grease at half normal speed with a DC 10 Balance check. Failure means it can’t move that
                    round (and must then make a Reflex save or fall), while failure by 5 or more means it falls (see the
                    Balance skill for details).
                    The spell can also be used to create a greasy coating on an item. Material objects not in use are
                    always affected by this spell, while an object wielded or employed by a creature receives a Reflex
                    saving throw to avoid the effect. If the initial saving throw fails, the creature immediately drops
                    the item. A saving throw must be made in each round that the creature attempts to pick up or use the
                    greased item. A creature wearing greased armor or clothing gains a +10 circumstance bonus on Escape
                    Artist checks and on grapple checks made to resist or escape a grapple or to escape a pin.
                    Material Component: A bit of pork rind or butter.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>2</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Mage Armor</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Creature touched</target>
                <duration>1 hour/level (D)</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless)</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>An invisible but tangible field of force surrounds the subject of a mage armor spell, providing a
                    +4 armor bonus to AC.
                    Unlike mundane armor, mage armor entails no armor check penalty, arcane spell failure chance, or
                    speed reduction. Since mage armor is made of force, incorporeal creatures can’t bypass it the way
                    they do normal armor.
                    Focus: A piece of cured leather.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Detect Magic</name>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>60 ft.</range>
                <area>Cone-shaped emanation</area>
                <duration>Concentration, up to 1 min./level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You detect magical auras. The amount of information revealed depends on how long you study a
                    particular area or subject.
                    1st Round: Presence or absence of magical auras.
                    2nd Round: Number of different magical auras and the power of the most potent aura.
                    3rd Round: The strength and location of each aura. If the items or creatures bearing the auras are
                    in line of sight, you can make Spellcraft skill checks to determine the school of magic involved in
                    each. (Make one check per aura; DC 15 + spell level, or 15 + half caster level for a nonspell
                    effect.)
                    Magical areas, multiple types of magic, or strong local magical emanations may distort or conceal
                    weaker auras.
                    Aura Strength: An aura’s power depends on a spell’s functioning spell level or an item’s caster
                    level. If an aura falls into more than one category, detect magic indicates the stronger of the two.
                    Lingering Aura: A magical aura lingers after its original source dissipates (in the case of a spell)
                    or is destroyed (in the case of a magic item). If detect magic is cast and directed at such a
                    location, the spell indicates an aura strength of dim (even weaker than a faint aura). How long the
                    aura lingers at this dim level depends on its original power:
                    Outsiders and elementals are not magical in themselves, but if they are summoned, the conjuration
                    spell registers.
                    Each round, you can turn to detect magic in a new area. The spell can penetrate barriers, but 1 foot
                    of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead, or 3 feet of wood or dirt blocks it.
                    Detect magic can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Scrying</name>
                <level>4</level>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, S, M/DF, F</components>
                <time>1 hour</time>
                <range>See text</range>
                <effect>Magical sensor</effect>
                <duration>1 min./level</duration>
                <save>Will negates</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>You can see and hear some creature, which may be at any distance. If the subject succeeds on a
                    Will save, the scrying attempt simply fails. The difficulty of the save depends on how well you know
                    the subject and what sort of physical connection (if any) you have to that creature. Furthermore, if
                    the subject is on another plane, it gets a +5 bonus on its Will save.
                    Knowledge Will Save Modifier
                    None +10
                    Secondhand (you have heard of the subject) +5
                    Firsthand (you have met the subject) +0
                    Familiar (you know the subject well) –5
                    1 You must have some sort of connection to a creature you have no knowledge of.
                    Connection Will Save Modifier
                    Likeness or picture –2
                    Possession or garment –4
                    Body part, lock of hair, bit of nail, etc. –10
                    If the save fails, you can see and hear the subject and the subject’s immediate surroundings
                    (approximately 10 feet in all directions of the subject). If the subject moves, the sensor follows
                    at a speed of up to 150 feet.
                    As with all divination (scrying) spells, the sensor has your full visual acuity, including any
                    magical effects. In addition, the following spells have a 5% chance per caster level of operating
                    through the sensor: detect chaos, detect evil, detect good, detect law, detect magic, and message.
                    If the save succeeds, you can’t attempt to scry on that subject again for at least 24 hours.
                    Arcane Material Component: The eye of a hawk, an eagle, or a roc, plus nitric acid, copper, and
                    zinc.
                    Wizard, Sorcerer, or Bard Focus: A mirror of finely wrought and highly polished silver costing not
                    less than 1,000 gp. The mirror must be at least 2 feet by 4 feet.
                    Cleric Focus: A holy water font costing not less than 100 gp.
                    Druid Focus: A natural pool of water.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>3</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>5</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Flare</name>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>Burst of light</effect>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Fortitude negates</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>This cantrip creates a burst of light. If you cause the light to burst directly in front of a
                    single creature, that creature is dazzled for 1 minute unless it makes a successful Fortitude save.
                    Sightless creatures, as well as creatures already dazzled, are not affected by flare.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Darkness</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, M/DF</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Object touched</target>
                <duration>10 min./level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell causes an object to radiate shadowy illumination out to a 20-foot radius. All creatures
                    in the area gain concealment (20% miss chance). Even creatures that can normally see in such
                    conditions (such as with darkvision or low-light vision) have the miss chance in an area shrouded in
                    magical darkness.
                    Normal lights (torches, candles, lanterns, and so forth) are incapable of brightening the area, as
                    are light spells of lower level. Higher level light spells are not affected by darkness.
                    If darkness is cast on a small object that is then placed inside or under a lightproof covering, the
                    spell’s effect is blocked until the covering is removed.
                    Darkness counters or dispels any light spell of equal or lower spell level.
                    Arcane Material Component: A bit of bat fur and either a drop of pitch or a piece of coal.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Ray of Frost</name>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>Ray</effect>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>A ray of freezing air and ice projects from your pointing finger. You must succeed on a ranged
                    touch attack with the ray to deal damage to a target. The ray deals 1d3 points of cold damage.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>2</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Magic Weapon</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S, DF</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Weapon touched</target>
                <duration>1 min./level</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless, object)</save>
                <sr>Yes (harmless, object)</sr>
                <text>Magic weapon gives a weapon a +1 enhancement bonus on attack and damage rolls. (An enhancement
                    bonus does not stack with a masterwork weapon’s +1 bonus on attack rolls.)
                    You can’t cast this spell on a natural weapon, such as an unarmed strike (instead, see magic fang).
                    A monk’s unarmed strike is considered a weapon, and thus it can be enhanced by this spell.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Paladin</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Disguise Self</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>6</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Personal</range>
                <target>You</target>
                <duration>10 min./level (D)</duration>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You make yourself—including clothing, armor, weapons, and equipment—look different. You can seem 1
                    foot shorter or taller, thin, fat, or in between. You cannot change your body type. Otherwise, the
                    extent of the apparent change is up to you. You could add or obscure a minor feature or look like an
                    entirely different person.
                    The spell does not provide the abilities or mannerisms of the chosen form, nor does it alter the
                    perceived tactile (touch) or audible (sound) properties of you or your equipment.
                    If you use this spell to create a disguise, you get a +10 bonus on the Disguise check.
                    A creature that interacts with the glamer gets a Will save to recognize it as an illusion.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Enlarge Person</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 round</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One humanoid creature</target>
                <duration>1 min./level (D)</duration>
                <save>Fortitude negates</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>This spell causes instant growth of a humanoid creature, doubling its height and multiplying its
                    weight by 8. This increase changes the creature’s size category to the next larger one. The target
                    gains a +2 size bonus to Strength, a –2 size penalty to Dexterity (to a minimum of 1), and a –1
                    penalty on attack rolls and AC due to its increased size.
                    A humanoid creature whose size increases to Large has a space of 10 feet and a natural reach of 10
                    feet. This spell does not change the target’s speed.
                    If insufficient room is available for the desired growth, the creature attains the maximum possible
                    size and may make a Strength check (using its increased Strength) to burst any enclosures in the
                    process. If it fails, it is constrained without harm by the materials enclosing it— the spell cannot
                    be used to crush a creature by increasing its size.
                    All equipment worn or carried by a creature is similarly enlarged by the spell. Melee and projectile
                    weapons affected by this spell deal more damage. Other magical properties are not affected by this
                    spell. Any enlarged item that leaves an enlarged creature’s possession (including a projectile or
                    thrown weapon) instantly returns to its normal size. This means that thrown weapons deal their
                    normal damage, and projectiles deal damage based on the size of the weapon that fired them. Magical
                    properties of enlarged items are not increased by this spell.
                    Multiple magical effects that increase size do not stack,.
                    Enlarge person counters and dispels reduce person.
                    Enlarge person can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                    Material Component: A pinch of powdered iron.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Feather Fall</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V</components>
                <time>1 free action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One Medium or smaller freefalling object or creature/level, no two of which may be more than 20
                    ft. apart
                </target>
                <duration>Until landing or 1 round/level</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless) or Will negates (object)</save>
                <sr>Yes (object)</sr>
                <text>The affected creatures or objects fall slowly. Feather fall instantly changes the rate at which
                    the targets fall to a mere 60 feet per round (equivalent to the end of a fall from a few feet), and
                    the subjects take no damage upon landing while the spell is in effect. However, when the spell
                    duration expires, a normal rate of falling resumes.
                    The spell affects one or more Medium or smaller creatures (including gear and carried objects up to
                    each creature’s maximum load) or objects, or the equivalent in larger creatures: A Large creature or
                    object counts as two Medium creatures or objects, a Huge creature or object counts as two Large
                    creatures or objects, and so forth.
                    You can cast this spell with an instant utterance, quickly enough to save yourself if you
                    unexpectedly fall. Casting the spell is a free action, like casting a quickened spell, and it counts
                    toward the normal limit of one quickened spell per round. You may even cast this spell when it isn’t
                    your turn.
                    This spell has no special effect on ranged weapons unless they are falling quite a distance. If the
                    spell is cast on a falling item the object does half normal damage based on its weight, with no
                    bonus for the height of the drop.
                    Feather fall works only upon free-falling objects. It does not affect a sword blow or a charging or
                    flying creature.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Web</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <effect>Webs in a 20-ft.-radius spread</effect>
                <duration>10 min./level (D)</duration>
                <save>Reflex negates; see text</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Web creates a many-layered mass of strong, sticky strands. These strands trap those caught in
                    them. The strands are similar to spider webs but far larger and tougher. These masses must be
                    anchored to two or more solid and diametrically opposed points or else the web collapses upon itself
                    and disappears. Creatures caught within a web become entangled among the gluey fibers. Attacking a
                    creature in a web won’t cause you to become entangled.
                    Anyone in the effect’s area when the spell is cast must make a Reflex save. If this save succeeds,
                    the creature is entangled, but not prevented from moving, though moving is more difficult than
                    normal for being entangled (see below). If the save fails, the creature is entangled and can’t move
                    from its space, but can break loose by spending 1 round and making a DC 20 Strength check or a DC 25
                    Escape Artist check. Once loose (either by making the initial Reflex save or a later Strength check
                    or Escape Artist check), a creature remains entangled, but may move through the web very slowly.
                    Each round devoted to moving allows the creature to make a new Strength check or Escape Artist
                    check. The creature moves 5 feet for each full 5 points by which the check result exceeds 10.
                    If you have at least 5 feet of web between you and an opponent, it provides cover. If you have at
                    least 20 feet of web between you, it provides total cover.
                    The strands of a web spell are flammable. A magic flaming sword can slash them away as easily as a
                    hand brushes away cobwebs. Any fire can set the webs alight and burn away 5 square feet in 1 round.
                    All creatures within flaming webs take 2d4 points of fire damage from the flames.
                    Web can be made permanent with a permanency spell. A permanent web that is damaged (but not
                    destroyed) regrows in 10 minutes.
                    Material Component: A bit of spider web.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Detect Poison</name>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One creature, one object, or a 5-ft. cube</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You determine whether a creature, object, or area has been poisoned or is poisonous. You can
                    determine the exact type of poison with a DC 20 Wisdom check. A character with the Craft (alchemy)
                    skill may try a DC 20 Craft (alchemy) check if the Wisdom check fails, or may try the Craft
                    (alchemy) check prior to the Wisdom check.
                    The spell can penetrate barriers, but 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead,
                    or 3 feet of wood or dirt blocks it.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Paladin</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Ranger</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Pyrotechnics</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Long (400 ft. + 40 ft./level)</range>
                <target>One fire source, up to a 20-ft. cube</target>
                <duration>1d4+1 rounds, or 1d4+1 rounds after creatures leave the smoke cloud; see text</duration>
                <save>Will negates or Fortitude negates; see text</save>
                <sr>Yes or No; see text</sr>
                <text>Pyrotechnics turns a fire into either a burst of blinding fireworks or a thick cloud of choking
                    smoke, depending on the version you choose.
                    Fireworks: The fireworks are a flashing, fiery, momentary burst of glowing, colored aerial lights.
                    This effect causes creatures within 120 feet of the fire source to become blinded for 1d4+1 rounds
                    (Will negates). These creatures must have line of sight to the fire to be affected. Spell resistance
                    can prevent blindness.
                    Smoke Cloud: A writhing stream of smoke billows out from the source, forming a choking cloud. The
                    cloud spreads 20 feet in all directions and lasts for 1 round per caster level. All sight, even
                    darkvision, is ineffective in or through the cloud. All within the cloud take –4 penalties to
                    Strength and Dexterity (Fortitude negates). These effects last for 1d4+1 rounds after the cloud
                    dissipates or after the creature leaves the area of the cloud. Spell resistance does not apply.
                    Material Component: The spell uses one fire source, which is immediately extinguished. A fire so
                    large that it exceeds a 20-foot cube is only partly extinguished. Magical fires are not
                    extinguished, although a fire-based creature used as a source takes 1 point of damage per caster
                    level.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Shield</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>1</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Personal</range>
                <target>You</target>
                <duration>1 min./level (D)</duration>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Shield creates an invisible, tower shield-sized mobile disk of force that hovers in front of you.
                    It negates magic missile attacks directed at you. The disk also provides a +4 shield bonus to AC.
                    This bonus applies against incorporeal touch attacks, since it is a force effect. The shield has no
                    armor check penalty or arcane spell failure chance. Unlike with a normal tower shield, you can’t use
                    the shield spell for cover.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Reduce Person</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 round</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One humanoid creature</target>
                <duration>1 min./level (D)</duration>
                <save>Fortitude negates</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>This spell causes instant diminution of a humanoid creature, halving its height, length, and width
                    and dividing its weight by 8. This decrease changes the creature’s size category to the next smaller
                    one. The target gains a +2 size bonus to Dexterity, a –2 size penalty to Strength (to a minimum of
                    1), and a +1 bonus on attack rolls and AC due to its reduced size.
                    A Small humanoid creature whose size decreases to Tiny has a space of 2-1/2 feet and a natural reach
                    of 0 feet (meaning that it must enter an opponent’s square to attack). A Large humanoid creature
                    whose size decreases to Medium has a space of 5 feet and a natural reach of 5 feet. This spell
                    doesn’t change the target’s speed.
                    All equipment worn or carried by a creature is similarly reduced by the spell.
                    Melee and projectile weapons deal less damage. Other magical properties are not affected by this
                    spell. Any reduced item that leaves the reduced creature’s possession (including a projectile or
                    thrown weapon) instantly returns to its normal size. This means that thrown weapons deal their
                    normal damage (projectiles deal damage based on the size of the weapon that fired them).
                    Multiple magical effects that reduce size do not stack.
                    Reduce person counters and dispels enlarge person.
                    Reduce person can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                    Material Component: A pinch of powdered iron.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Alarm</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>1</school>
                <components>V, S, F/DF</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <area>20-ft.-radius emanation centered on a point in space</area>
                <duration>2 hours/level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Alarm sounds a mental or audible alarm each time a creature of Tiny or larger size enters the
                    warded area or touches it. A creature that speaks the password (determined by you at the time of
                    casting) does not set off the alarm. You decide at the time of casting whether the alarm will be
                    mental or audible.
                    Mental Alarm: A mental alarm alerts you (and only you) so long as you remain within 1 mile of the
                    warded area. You note a single mental “ping” that awakens you from normal sleep but does not
                    otherwise disturb concentration. A silence spell has no effect on a mental alarm.
                    Audible Alarm: An audible alarm produces the sound of a hand bell, and anyone within 60 feet of the
                    warded area can hear it clearly. Reduce the distance by 10 feet for each interposing closed door and
                    by 20 feet for each substantial interposing wall.
                    In quiet conditions, the ringing can be heard faintly as far as 180 feet away. The sound lasts for 1
                    round. Creatures within a silence spell cannot hear the ringing.
                    Ethereal or astral creatures do not trigger the alarm.
                    Alarm can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                    Arcane Focus: A tiny bell and a piece of very fine silver wire
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Ranger</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Spider Climb</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Creature touched</target>
                <duration>10 min./level</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless)</save>
                <sr>Yes (harmless)</sr>
                <text>The subject can climb and travel on vertical surfaces or even traverse ceilings as well as a
                    spider does. The affected creature must have its hands free to climb in this manner. The subject
                    gains a climb speed of 20 feet; furthermore, it need not make Climb checks to traverse a vertical or
                    horizontal surface (even upside down). A spider climbing creature retains its Dexterity bonus to
                    Armor Class (if any) while climbing, and opponents get no special bonus to their attacks against it.
                    It cannot, however, use the run action while climbing.
                    Material Component: A drop of bitumen and a live spider, both of which must be eaten by the subject.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Hold Portal</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>1</school>
                <components>V</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <target>One portal, up to 20 sq. ft./level</target>
                <duration>1 min./level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell magically holds shut a door, gate, window, or shutter of wood, metal, or stone. The
                    magic affects the portal just as if it were securely closed and normally locked. A knock spell or a
                    successful dispel magic spell can negate a hold portal spell.
                    For a portal affected by this spell, add 5 to the normal DC for forcing open the portal.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>True Strike</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Personal</range>
                <target>You</target>
                <duration>See text</duration>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You gain temporary, intuitive insight into the immediate future during your next attack. Your next
                    single attack roll (if it is made before the end of the next round) gains a +20 insight bonus.
                    Additionally, you are not affected by the miss chance that applies to attackers trying to strike a
                    concealed target.
                    Focus: A small wooden replica of an archery target.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Scorching Ray</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>One or more rays</effect>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>You blast your enemies with fiery rays. You may fire one ray, plus one additional ray for every
                    four levels beyond 3rd (to a maximum of three rays at 11th level). Each ray requires a ranged touch
                    attack to hit and deals 4d6 points of fire damage.
                    The rays may be fired at the same or different targets, but all bolts must be aimed at targets
                    within 30 feet of each other and fired simultaneously.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Arcane Lock</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>1</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>The door, chest, or portal touched, up to 30 sq. ft./level in size</target>
                <duration>Permanent</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>An arcane lock spell cast upon a door, chest, or portal magically locks it. You can freely pass
                    your own arcane lock without affecting it; otherwise, a door or object secured with this spell can
                    be opened only by breaking in or with a successful dispel magic or knock spell. Add 10 to the normal
                    DC to break open a door or portal affected by this spell. (A knock spell does not remove an arcane
                    lock; it only suppresses the effect for 10 minutes.)
                    Material Component: Gold dust worth 25 gp.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Stinking Cloud</name>
                <level>3</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <effect>Cloud spreads in 20-ft. radius, 20 ft. high</effect>
                <duration>1 round/level</duration>
                <save>Fortitude negates; see text</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Stinking cloud creates a bank of fog like that created by fog cloud, except that the vapors are
                    nauseating. Living creatures in the cloud become nauseated. This condition lasts as long as the
                    creature is in the cloud and for 1d4+1 rounds after it leaves. (Roll separately for each nauseated
                    character.) Any creature that succeeds on its save but remains in the cloud must continue to save
                    each round on your turn.
                    Stinking cloud can be made permanent with a permanency spell. A permanent stinking cloud dispersed
                    by wind reforms in 10 minutes.
                    Material Component: A rotten egg or several skunk cabbage leaves.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>3</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>3</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Identify</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, S, M/DF</components>
                <time>1 hour</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>One touched object</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>The spell determines all magic properties of a single magic item, including how to activate those
                    functions (if appropriate), and how many charges are left (if any).
                    Identify does not function when used on an artifact.
                    Arcane Material Component: A pearl of at least 100 gp value, crushed and stirred into wine with an
                    owl feather; the infusion must be drunk prior to spellcasting.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Flaming Sphere</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S, M/DF</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <effect>5-ft.-diameter sphere</effect>
                <duration>1 round/level</duration>
                <save>Reflex negates</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>A burning globe of fire rolls in whichever direction you point and burns those it strikes. It
                    moves 30 feet per round. As part of this movement, it can ascend or jump up to 30 feet to strike a
                    target. If it enters a space with a creature, it stops moving for the round and deals 2d6 points of
                    fire damage to that creature, though a successful Reflex save negates that damage. A flaming sphere
                    rolls over barriers less than 4 feet tall. It ignites flammable substances it touches and
                    illuminates the same area as a torch would.
                    The sphere moves as long as you actively direct it (a move action for you); otherwise, it merely
                    stays at rest and burns. It can be extinguished by any means that would put out a normal fire of its
                    size. The surface of the sphere has a spongy, yielding consistency and so does not cause damage
                    except by its flame. It cannot push aside unwilling creatures or batter down large obstacles. A
                    flaming sphere winks out if it exceeds the spell’s range.
                    Arcane Material Component: A bit of tallow, a pinch of brimstone, and a dusting of powdered iron.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Resistance</name>
                <school>1</school>
                <components>V, S, M/DF</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Creature touched</target>
                <duration>1 minute</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless)</save>
                <sr>Yes (harmless)</sr>
                <text>You imbue the subject with magical energy that protects it from harm, granting it a +1 resistance
                    bonus on saves.
                    Resistance can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                    Arcane Material Component: A miniature cloak.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Paladin</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Comprehend Languages</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, S, M/DF</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Personal</range>
                <target>You</target>
                <duration>10 min./level</duration>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You can understand the spoken words of creatures or read otherwise incomprehensible written
                    messages. In either case, you must touch the creature or the writing. The ability to read does not
                    necessarily impart insight into the material, merely its literal meaning. The spell enables you to
                    understand or read an unknown language, not speak or write it.
                    Written material can be read at the rate of one page (250 words) per minute. Magical writing cannot
                    be read, though the spell reveals that it is magical. This spell can be foiled by certain warding
                    magic (such as the secret page and illusory script spells). It does not decipher codes or reveal
                    messages concealed in otherwise normal text.
                    Comprehend languages can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                    Arcane Material Component: A pinch of soot and a few grains of salt.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <name>Wall of Smoke</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>Standard Action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>A straight wall whose area is 10 foot square per level</effect>
                <duration>1 round/level</duration>
                <save>fortitude</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell creates a thin wall of black smoke. The wall is stationary once created. The wall
                    blocks sight to a limited degree. Creatures on opposite sides of the wall that cannot see over it
                    gain concealment from each other. A creature can pass through the wall, but must make a fort save to
                    avoid being nauseated for 1 round.

                    A moderate wind (11+ mpg), such as from a gust of wind spell, destroys the wall in one round. Does
                    not function under water.
                </text>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Fireball</name>
                <level>3</level>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Long (400 ft. + 40 ft./level)</range>
                <area>20-ft.-radius spread</area>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Reflex half</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>A fireball spell is an explosion of flame that detonates with a low roar and deals 1d6 points of
                    fire damage per caster level (maximum 10d6) to every creature within the area. Unattended objects
                    also take this damage. The explosion creates almost no pressure.
                    You point your finger and determine the range (distance and height) at which the fireball is to
                    burst. A glowing, pea-sized bead streaks from the pointing digit and, unless it impacts upon a
                    material body or solid barrier prior to attaining the prescribed range, blossoms into the fireball
                    at that point. (An early impact results in an early detonation.) If you attempt to send the bead
                    through a narrow passage, such as through an arrow slit, you must “hit” the opening with a ranged
                    touch attack, or else the bead strikes the barrier and detonates prematurely.
                    The fireball sets fire to combustibles and damages objects in the area. It can melt metals with low
                    melting points, such as lead, gold, copper, silver, and bronze. If the damage caused to an
                    interposing barrier shatters or breaks through it, the fireball may continue beyond the barrier if
                    the area permits; otherwise it stops at the barrier just as any other spell effect does.
                    Material Component: A tiny ball of bat guano and sulfur.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>3</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>3</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Haste</name>
                <level>3</level>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One creature/level, no two of which can be more than 30 ft. apart</target>
                <duration>1 round/level</duration>
                <save>Fortitude negates (harmless)</save>
                <sr>Yes (harmless)</sr>
                <text>The transmuted creatures move and act more quickly than normal. This extra speed has several
                    effects.
                    When making a full attack action, a hasted creature may make one extra attack with any weapon he is
                    holding. The attack is made using the creature’s full base attack bonus, plus any modifiers
                    appropriate to the situation. (This effect is not cumulative with similar effects, such as that
                    provided by a weapon of speed, nor does it actually grant an extra action, so you can’t use it to
                    cast a second spell or otherwise take an extra action in the round.)
                    A hasted creature gains a +1 bonus on attack rolls and a +1 dodge bonus to AC and Reflex saves. Any
                    condition that makes you lose your Dexterity bonus to Armor Class (if any) also makes you lose dodge
                    bonuses.
                    All of the hasted creature’s modes of movement (including land movement, burrow, climb, fly, and
                    swim) increase by 30 feet, to a maximum of twice the subject’s normal speed using that form of
                    movement. This increase counts as an enhancement bonus, and it affects the creature’s jumping
                    distance as normal for increased speed.
                    Multiple haste effects don’t stack. Haste dispels and counters slow.
                    Material Component: A shaving of licorice root.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>3</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>3</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>3</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Mount</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 round</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>One mount</effect>
                <duration>2 hours/level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You summon a light horse or a pony (your choice) to serve you as a mount. The steed serves
                    willingly and well. The mount comes with a bit and bridle and a riding saddle.
                    Material Component: A bit of horse hair.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Knock</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <target>One door, box, or chest with an area of up to 10 sq. ft./level</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous; see text</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>The knock spell opens stuck, barred, locked, held, or arcane locked doors. It opens secret doors,
                    as well as locked or trick-opening boxes or chests. It also loosens welds, shackles, or chains
                    (provided they serve to hold closures shut). If used to open a arcane locked door, the spell does
                    not remove the arcane lock but simply suspends its functioning for 10 minutes. In all other cases,
                    the door does not relock itself or become stuck again on its own. Knock does not raise barred gates
                    or similar impediments (such as a portcullis), nor does it affect ropes, vines, and the like. The
                    effect is limited by the area. Each spell can undo as many as two means of preventing egress.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Invisibility, Greater</name>
                <level>4</level>
                <school>6</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Personal or touch</range>
                <target>You or creature touched</target>
                <duration>1 round/level (D)</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless)</save>
                <sr>Yes (harmless) or Yes (harmless, object)</sr>
                <text>This spell functions like invisibility, except that it doesn’t end if the subject attacks.</text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>4</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>2</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Silent Image</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>6</school>
                <components>V, S, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Long (400 ft. + 40 ft./level)</range>
                <effect>Visual figment that cannot extend beyond four 10-ft. cubes + one 10-ft. cube/level (S)</effect>
                <duration>Concentration</duration>
                <save>Will disbelief (if interacted with)</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell creates the visual illusion of an object, creature, or force, as visualized by you. The
                    illusion does not create sound, smell, texture, or temperature. You can move the image within the
                    limits of the size of the effect.
                    Focus: A bit of fleece.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Mending</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>10 ft.</range>
                <target>One object of up to 1 lb.</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless, object)</save>
                <sr>Yes (harmless, object)</sr>
                <text>Mending repairs small breaks or tears in objects (but not warps, such as might be caused by a warp
                    wood spell). It will weld broken metallic objects such as a ring, a chain link, a medallion, or a
                    slender dagger, providing but one break exists.
                    Ceramic or wooden objects with multiple breaks can be invisibly rejoined to be as strong as new. A
                    hole in a leather sack or a wineskin is completely healed over by mending. The spell can repair a
                    magic item, but the item’s magical abilities are not restored. The spell cannot mend broken magic
                    rods, staffs, or wands, nor does it affect creatures (including constructs).
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Alter Self</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Personal</range>
                <target>You</target>
                <duration>10 min./level (D)</duration>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You assume the form of a creature of the same type as your normal form. The new form must be
                    within one size category of your normal size. The maximum HD of an assumed form is equal to your
                    caster level, to a maximum of 5 HD at 5th level. You can change into a member of your own kind or
                    even into yourself.
                    You retain your own ability scores. Your class and level, hit points, alignment, base attack bonus,
                    and base save bonuses all remain the same. You retain all supernatural and spell-like special
                    attacks and qualities of your normal form, except for those requiring a body part that the new form
                    does not have (such as a mouth for a breath weapon or eyes for a gaze attack).
                    You keep all extraordinary special attacks and qualities derived from class levels, but you lose any
                    from your normal form that are not derived from class levels.
                    If the new form is capable of speech, you can communicate normally. You retain any spellcasting
                    ability you had in your original form, but the new form must be able to speak intelligibly (that is,
                    speak a language) to use verbal components and must have limbs capable of fine manipulation to use
                    somatic or material components.
                    You acquire the physical qualities of the new form while retaining your own mind. Physical qualities
                    include natural size, mundane movement capabilities (such as burrowing, climbing, walking, swimming,
                    and flight with wings, to a maximum speed of 120 feet for flying or 60 feet for nonflying movement),
                    natural armor bonus, natural weapons (such as claws, bite, and so on), racial skill bonuses, racial
                    bonus feats, and any gross physical qualities (presence or absence of wings, number of extremities,
                    and so forth). A body with extra limbs does not allow you to make more attacks (or more advantageous
                    two-weapon attacks) than normal.
                    You do not gain any extraordinary special attacks or special qualities not noted above under
                    physical qualities, such as darkvision, low-light vision, blindsense, blindsight, fast healing,
                    regeneration, scent, and so forth.
                    You do not gain any supernatural special attacks, special qualities, or spell-like abilities of the
                    new form. Your creature type and subtype (if any) remain the same regardless of your new form. You
                    cannot take the form of any creature with a template, even if that template doesn’t change the
                    creature type or subtype.
                    You can freely designate the new form’s minor physical qualities (such as hair color, hair texture,
                    and skin color) within the normal ranges for a creature of that kind. The new form’s significant
                    physical qualities (such as height, weight, and gender) are also under your control, but they must
                    fall within the norms for the new form’s kind. You are effectively disguised as an average member of
                    the new form’s race. If you use this spell to create a disguise, you get a +10 bonus on your
                    Disguise check.
                    When the change occurs, your equipment, if any, either remains worn or held by the new form (if it
                    is capable of wearing or holding the item), or melds into the new form and becomes nonfunctional.
                    When you revert to your true form, any objects previously melded into the new form reappear in the
                    same location on your body they previously occupied and are once again functional. Any new items you
                    wore in the assumed form and can’t wear in your normal form fall off and land at your feet; any that
                    you could wear in either form or carry in a body part common to both forms at the time of reversion
                    are still held in the same way. Any part of the body or piece of equipment that is separated from
                    the whole reverts to its true form.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Color Spray</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>6</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>15 ft.</range>
                <area>Cone-shaped burst</area>
                <duration>Instantaneous; see text</duration>
                <save>Will negates</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>A vivid cone of clashing colors springs forth from your hand, causing creatures to become stunned,
                    perhaps also blinded, and possibly knocking them unconscious.
                    Each creature within the cone is affected according to its Hit Dice.
                    2 HD or less: The creature is unconscious, blinded, and stunned for 2d4 rounds, then blinded and
                    stunned for 1d4 rounds, and then stunned for 1 round. (Only living creatures are knocked
                    unconscious.)
                    3 or 4 HD: The creature is blinded and stunned for 1d4 rounds, then stunned for 1 round.
                    5 or more HD: The creature is stunned for 1 round.
                    Sightless creatures are not affected by color spray.
                    Material Component: A pinch each of powder or sand that is colored red, yellow, and blue.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Arcane Mark</name>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>0 ft.</range>
                <effect>One personal rune or mark, all of which must fit within 1 sq. ft.</effect>
                <duration>Permanent</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell allows you to inscribe your personal rune or mark, which can consist of no more than
                    six characters. The writing can be visible or invisible. An arcane mark spell enables you to etch
                    the rune upon any substance without harm to the material upon which it is placed. If an invisible
                    mark is made, a detect magic spell causes it to glow and be visible, though not necessarily
                    understandable.
                    See invisibility, true seeing, a gem of seeing, or a robe of eyes likewise allows the user to see an
                    invisible arcane mark. A read magic spell reveals the words, if any. The mark cannot be dispelled,
                    but it can be removed by the caster or by an erase spell.
                    If an arcane mark is placed on a living being, normal wear gradually causes the effect to fade in
                    about a month.
                    Arcane mark must be cast on an object prior to casting instant summons on the same object (see that
                    spell description for details).
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Lightning Bolt</name>
                <level>3</level>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>120 ft.</range>
                <area>120-ft. line</area>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Reflex half</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>You release a powerful stroke of electrical energy that deals 1d6 points of electricity damage per
                    caster level (maximum 10d6) to each creature within its area. The bolt begins at your fingertips.
                    The lightning bolt sets fire to combustibles and damages objects in its path. It can melt metals
                    with a low melting point, such as lead, gold, copper, silver, or bronze. If the damage caused to an
                    interposing barrier shatters or breaks through it, the bolt may continue beyond the barrier if the
                    spell’s range permits; otherwise, it stops at the barrier just as any other spell effect does.
                    Material Component: A bit of fur and an amber, crystal, or glass rod.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>3</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>3</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Ghost Sound</name>
                <school>6</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>Illusory sounds</effect>
                <duration>1 round/level (D)</duration>
                <save>Will disbelief (if interacted with)</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Ghost sound allows you to create a volume of sound that rises, recedes, approaches, or remains at
                    a fixed place. You choose what type of sound ghost sound creates when casting it and cannot
                    thereafter change the sound’s basic character.
                    The volume of sound created depends on your level. You can produce as much noise as four normal
                    humans per caster level (maximum twenty humans). Thus, talking, singing, shouting, walking,
                    marching, or running sounds can be created. The noise a ghost sound spell produces can be virtually
                    any type of sound within the volume limit. A horde of rats running and squeaking is about the same
                    volume as eight humans running and shouting. A roaring lion is equal to the noise from sixteen
                    humans, while a roaring dire tiger is equal to the noise from twenty humans.
                    Ghost sound can enhance the effectiveness of a silent image spell.
                    Ghost sound can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                    Material Component: A bit of wool or a small lump of wax.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <name>Regroup</name>
                <level>3</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</time>
                <range>Close</range>
                <target>1/ Level</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You teleport your companions to your side. Each subject of this spell teleports to a square
                    adjacent to you. If those squares are occupied or cannot support the teleported creatures, the
                    creatures appear as close to you as possible, on a surface that can support them, in an unoccupied
                    square.
                </text>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Burning Hands</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>15 ft.</range>
                <area>Cone-shaped burst</area>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Reflex half</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>A cone of searing flame shoots from your fingertips. Any creature in the area of the flames takes
                    1d4 points of fire damage per caster level (maximum 5d4). Flammable materials burn if the flames
                    touch them. A character can extinguish burning items as a full-round action.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Melf’s Acid Arrow</name>
                <level>2</level>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S, M, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Long (400 ft. + 40 ft./level)</range>
                <effect>One arrow of acid</effect>
                <duration>1 round + 1 round per three levels</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>A magical arrow of acid springs from your hand and speeds to its target. You must succeed on a
                    ranged touch attack to hit your target. The arrow deals 2d4 points of acid damage with no splash
                    damage. For every three caster levels (to a maximum of 18th), the acid, unless somehow neutralized,
                    lasts for another round, dealing another 2d4 points of damage in that round.
                    Material Component: Powdered rhubarb leaf and an adder’s stomach.
                    Focus: A dart.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>2</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
        </class>
        <class>
            <id>1114</id>
            <prestige>1</prestige>
            <name>Loremaster</name>
            <level>2</level>
            <hd>0</hd>
            <skills>Appraise, Concentration, Craft (alchemy), Decipher Script, Gather Information, Handle Animal, Heal,
                Knowledge, Perform, Profession, Speak Language, Spellcraft, Use Magic Device
            </skills>
            <skillPoints>4</skillPoints>
            <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
            <will>3</will>
            <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            <slotsCurrent>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slotsCurrent>
            <feat>
                <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                <text>Loremasters gain no proficiency with any weapon or armor.</text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Spells per Day/Spells Known</name>
                <text>When a new loremaster level is gained, the character gains new spells per day (and spells known,
                    if applicable) as if she had also gained a level in a spellcasting class she belonged to before she
                    added the prestige class. She does not, however, gain any other benefit a character of that class
                    would have gained. This essentially means that she adds the level of loremaster to the level of some
                    other spellcasting class the character has, then determines spells per day, spells known, and caster
                    level accordingly.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Secret</name>
                <text>At 1st level and every two levels higher than 1st (3rd, 5th, 7th, and 9th), the loremaster chooses
                    one secret from the table below. Her loremaster level plus Intelligence modifier determines the
                    secrets from which she can choose. She can’t choose the same secret twice.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Lore</name>
                <text>At 2nd level, a loremaster gains the ability to know legends or information regarding various
                    topics, just as a bard can with bardic knowledge. The loremaster adds her level and her Intelligence
                    modifier to the lore check, which functions otherwise exactly like a bardic knowledge check.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Fort Save Secret</name>
                <modifier>
                    <type>15</type>
                    <value>2</value>
                </modifier>
            </feat>
            <autolevel>
                <will>2</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                    <text>Loremasters gain no proficiency with any weapon or armor.</text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Spells per Day/Spells Known</name>
                    <text>When a new loremaster level is gained, the character gains new spells per day (and spells
                        known, if applicable) as if she had also gained a level in a spellcasting class she belonged to
                        before she added the prestige class. She does not, however, gain any other benefit a character
                        of that class would have gained. This essentially means that she adds the level of loremaster to
                        the level of some other spellcasting class the character has, then determines spells per day,
                        spells known, and caster level accordingly.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Secret</name>
                    <text>At 1st level and every two levels higher than 1st (3rd, 5th, 7th, and 9th), the loremaster
                        chooses one secret from the table below. Her loremaster level plus Intelligence modifier
                        determines the secrets from which she can choose. She can’t choose the same secret twice.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>2</level>
                <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Lore</name>
                    <text>At 2nd level, a loremaster gains the ability to know legends or information regarding various
                        topics, just as a bard can with bardic knowledge. The loremaster adds her level and her
                        Intelligence modifier to the lore check, which functions otherwise exactly like a bardic
                        knowledge check.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>3</level>
                <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>4</level>
                <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Languages</name>
                    <text>A loremaster can choose any new language at 4th level.</text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>5</level>
                <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>6</level>
                <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>5</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Greater Lore (Ex)</name>
                    <text>At 6th level, a loremaster gains the ability to understand magic items, as with the identify
                        spell.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>7</level>
                <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>5</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>8</level>
                <baseAttack>4</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>6</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Languages</name>
                    <text>A loremaster can choose any new language at 8th level.</text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>9</level>
                <baseAttack>4</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>6</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>10</level>
                <baseAttack>5</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>7</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>True Lore (Ex)</name>
                    <text>At 10th level, once per day a loremaster can use her knowledge to gain the effect of a legend
                        lore spell or an analyze dweomer spell.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>11</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>12</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>13</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>14</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>15</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>16</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>17</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>18</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>19</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>20</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <skills>Appraise, Concentration, Craft (alchemy), Decipher Script, Gather Information, Handle Animal, Heal,
                Knowledge, Perform, Profession, Speak Language, Spellcraft, Use Magic Device
            </skills>
        </class>
        <class>
            <id>1120</id>
            <prestige>1</prestige>
            <name>Shadowcraft Mage</name>
            <hd>0</hd>
            <skills>Concentration, Craft, Knowledge, Profession, Search, Spellcraft</skills>
            <will>2</will>
            <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            <slotsCurrent>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slotsCurrent>
            <feat>
                <name>Spells per Day/Spells Known</name>
                <text>When a new archmage level is gained, the character gains new spells per day (and spells known, if
                    applicable) as if he had also gained a level in whatever arcane spellcasting class in which he could
                    cast 7th-level spells before he added the prestige class level. He does not, however, gain any other
                    benefit a character of that class would have gained. If a character had more than one arcane
                    spellcasting class in which he could cast 7th-level spells before he became an archmage, he must
                    decide to which class he adds each level of archmage for the purpose of determining spells per day.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <autolevel>
                <will>2</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                    <text>Archmages gain no proficiency with any weapon or armor.</text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Spells per Day/Spells Known</name>
                    <text>When a new archmage level is gained, the character gains new spells per day (and spells known,
                        if applicable) as if he had also gained a level in whatever arcane spellcasting class in which
                        he could cast 7th-level spells before he added the prestige class level. He does not, however,
                        gain any other benefit a character of that class would have gained. If a character had more than
                        one arcane spellcasting class in which he could cast 7th-level spells before he became an
                        archmage, he must decide to which class he adds each level of archmage for the purpose of
                        determining spells per day.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>High Arcana</name>
                    <text>An archmage gains the opportunity to select a special ability from among those described below
                        by permanently eliminating one existing spell slot (she cannot eliminate a spell slot of higher
                        level than the highest-level spell she can cast). Each special ability has a minimum required
                        spell slot level, as specified in its description.
                        An archmage may choose to eliminate a spell slot of a higher level than that required to gain a
                        type of high arcana.
                        Arcane Fire (Su)
                        The archmage gains the ability to change arcane spell energy into arcane fire, manifesting it as
                        a bolt of raw magical energy. The bolt is a ranged touch attack with long range (400 feet + 40
                        feet/level of archmage) that deals 1d6 points of damage per class level of the archmage plus 1d6
                        points of damage per level of the spell used to create the effect. This ability costs one
                        9th-level spell slot.
                        Arcane Reach (Su)
                        The archmage can use spells with a range of touch on a target up to 30 feet away. The archmage
                        must make a ranged touch attack. Arcane reach can be selected a second time as a special
                        ability, in which case the range increases to 60 feet. This ability costs one 7th-level spell
                        slot.
                        Mastery of Counterspelling
                        When the archmage counterspells a spell, it is turned back upon the caster as if it were fully
                        affected by a spell turning spell. If the spell cannot be affected by spell turning, then it is
                        merely counterspelled. This ability costs one 7th-level spell slot.
                        Mastery of Elements
                        The archmage can alter an arcane spell when cast so that it utilizes a different element from
                        the one it normally uses. This ability can only alter a spell with the acid, cold, fire,
                        electricity, or sonic descriptor. The spell’s casting time is unaffected. The caster decides
                        whether to alter the spell’s energy type and chooses the new energy type when he begins casting.
                        This ability costs one 8th-level spell slot.
                        Mastery of Shaping
                        The archmage can alter area and effect spells that use one of the following shapes: burst, cone,
                        cylinder, emanation, or spread. The alteration consists of creating spaces within the spell’s
                        area or effect that are not subject to the spell. The minimum dimension for these spaces is a
                        5-foot cube. Furthermore, any shapeable spells have a minimum dimension of 5 feet instead of 10
                        feet. This ability costs one 6th-level spell slot.
                        Spell Power
                        This ability increases the archmage’s effective caster level by +1 (for purposes of determining
                        level-dependent spell variables such as damage dice or range, and caster level checks only).
                        This ability costs one 5th-level spell slot.
                        Spell-Like Ability
                        An archmage who selects this type of high arcana can use one of her arcane spell slots (other
                        than a slot expended to learn this or any other type of high arcana) to permanently prepare one
                        of her arcane spells as a spell-like ability that can be used twice per day. The archmage does
                        not use any components when casting the spell, although a spell that costs XP to cast still does
                        so and a spell with a costly material component instead costs her 10 times that amount in XP.
                        This ability costs one 5th-level spell slot.
                        The spell-like ability normally uses a spell slot of the spell’s level, although the archmage
                        can choose to make a spell modified by a metamagic feat into a spell-like ability at the
                        appropriate spell level.
                        The archmage may use an available higher-level spell slot in order to use the spell-like ability
                        more often. Using a slot three levels higher than the chosen spell allows her to use the
                        spell-like ability four times per day, and a slot six levels higher lets her use it six times
                        per day.
                        If spell-like ability is selected more than one time as a high arcana choice, this ability can
                        apply to the same spell chosen the first time (increasing the number of times per day it can be
                        used) or to a different spell.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>2</level>
                <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>3</level>
                <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>4</level>
                <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>5</level>
                <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>6</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>7</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>8</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>9</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>10</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>11</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>12</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>13</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>14</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>15</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>16</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>17</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>18</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>19</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>20</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <skills>Concentration, Craft, Knowledge, Profession, Search, Spellcraft</skills>
        </class>
        <skill>
            <name>Appraise</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>1</skillID>
            <name>Balance</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>2</skillID>
            <name>Bluff</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>4</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>3</skillID>
            <name>Climb</name>
            <ability>1</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>4</skillID>
            <name>Concentration</name>
            <ability>3</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>13</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>5</skillID>
            <name>Craft</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>6</skillID>
            <name>Decipher Script</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>7</skillID>
            <name>Diplomacy</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>8</skillID>
            <name>Disable Device</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>9</skillID>
            <name>Disguise</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>10</skillID>
            <name>Escape Artist</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>11</skillID>
            <name>Forgery</name>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>12</skillID>
            <name>Gather Information</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>5</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>13</skillID>
            <name>Handle Animal</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>14</skillID>
            <name>Heal</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>15</skillID>
            <name>Hide</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>6</rank>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>16</skillID>
            <name>Intimidate</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>17</skillID>
            <name>Jump</name>
            <ability>1</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>18</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (arcana)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>13</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>19</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (architecture)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>10</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>20</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (dungeoneering)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>5</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>21</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (geography)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>22</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (history)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>5</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>23</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (local)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>24</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (nature)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>25</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (nobility)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>27</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (planes)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>5</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>26</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (religion)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>28</skillID>
            <name>Listen</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>29</skillID>
            <name>Move Silently</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>30</skillID>
            <name>Open Lock</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>31</skillID>
            <name>Perform</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>3</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>32</skillID>
            <name>Profession</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>33</skillID>
            <name>Ride</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>34</skillID>
            <name>Search</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>35</skillID>
            <name>Sense Motive</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>36</skillID>
            <name>Sleight of Hand</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>37</skillID>
            <name>Speak Language</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>14</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>38</skillID>
            <name>Spellcraft</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>13</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>39</skillID>
            <name>Spot</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>40</skillID>
            <name>Survival</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>41</skillID>
            <name>Swim</name>
            <ability>1</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>2</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>42</skillID>
            <name>Tumble</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>43</skillID>
            <name>Use Magic Device</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>44</skillID>
            <name>Use Rope</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
        </skill>
        <skillPoints>14</skillPoints>
        <xp>46117</xp>
        <abilities>10,14,16,16,18,7,13,</abilities>
        <hpMax>76</hpMax>
        <hpCurrent>68</hpCurrent>
        <feat>
            <name>Combat Casting</name>
            <text>You get a +4 bonus on Concentration checks made to cast a spell or use a spell-like ability while on
                the defensive or while you are grappling or pinned.
            </text>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Scribe Scroll</name>
            <text>You can create a scroll of any spell that you know. Scribing a scroll takes one day for each 1,000 gp
                in its base price. The base price of a scroll is its spell level x its caster level x 25 gp. To scribe a
                scroll, you must spend 1/25 of this base price in XP and use up raw materials costing one-half of this
                base price.
                Any scroll that stores a spell with a costly material component or an XP cost also carries a
                commensurate cost. In addition to the costs derived from the base price, you must expend the material
                component or pay the XP when scribing the scroll.
            </text>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Craft Wand</name>
            <text>You can create a wand of any 4th-level or lower spell that you know. Crafting a wand takes one day for
                each 1,000 gp in its base price. The base price of a wand is its caster level x the spell level x 750
                gp. To craft a wand, you must spend 1/25 of this base price in XP and use up raw materials costing
                one-half of this base price. A newly created wand has 50 charges.
                Any wand that stores a spell with a costly material component or an XP cost also carries a commensurate
                cost. In addition to the cost derived from the base price, you must expend fifty copies of the material
                component or pay fifty times the XP cost.
            </text>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Craft Wonderous Item</name>
            <text>You can create any wondrous item whose prerequisites you meet. Enchanting a wondrous item takes one
                day for each 1,000 gp in its price. To enchant a wondrous item, you must spend 1/25 of the item’s price
                in XP and use up raw materials costing half of this price.
                You can also mend a broken wondrous item if it is one that you could make. Doing so costs half the XP,
                half the raw materials, and half the time it would take to craft that item in the first place.
                Some wondrous items incur extra costs in material components or XP, as noted in their descriptions.
                These costs are in addition to those derived from the item’s base price. You must pay such a cost to
                create an item or to mend a broken one.
            </text>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Alertness</name>
            <text>You get a +2 bonus on all Listen checks and Spot checks.</text>
            <modifier>
                <category>2</category>
                <type>28</type>
                <value>2</value>
            </modifier>
            <modifier>
                <category>2</category>
                <type>39</type>
                <value>2</value>
            </modifier>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Weasel Reflexes</name>
            <text>You get a +2 bonus on all Reflex saving throws.</text>
            <modifier>
                <type>16</type>
                <value>2</value>
            </modifier>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Skill Focus</name>
            <text>You get a +3 bonus on all checks involving that skill.</text>
            <modifier>
                <category>2</category>
                <type>18</type>
                <value>3</value>
            </modifier>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Spell Focus (illusion)</name>
            <text>Add +1 to the Difficulty Class for all saving throws against spells from the school of magic you
                select.
            </text>
        </feat>
        <action>
            <name>Longspear</name>
            <attack>%9</attack>
            <damage>1d6+1</damage>
            <critMult>3</critMult>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Sling</name>
            <attack>%10</attack>
            <damage>1n3+1</damage>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Whip</name>
            <attack>%9</attack>
            <damage>1n2+1</damage>
        </action>
        <item>
            <name>Ring Of Protection +1</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <type>10</type>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
            <modifier>
                <type>14</type>
                <value>1</value>
            </modifier>
        </item>
        <item>
            <name>Ring Of Wizardry (1)</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <type>10</type>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
        </item>
        <item>
            <name>Bracers Of Armor +1</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <type>15</type>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
            <modifier>
                <type>10</type>
                <value>1</value>
            </modifier>
        </item>
        <item>
            <name>Boots Of Spiderclimb</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <type>15</type>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
        </item>
        <item>
            <name>Vest of Resistance +2</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
            <value>4000.0</value>
            <modifier>
                <type>15</type>
                <value>2</value>
            </modifier>
            <modifier>
                <type>16</type>
                <value>2</value>
            </modifier>
            <modifier>
                <type>17</type>
                <value>2</value>
            </modifier>
        </item>
        <item>
            <name>Brooch Of Shielding 23</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
        </item>
        <container>
            <name>Weapons</name>
            <item>
                <name>Longspear (Cold Iron)</name>
                <type>6</type>
                <damage>1d6</damage>
                <damageType>2</damageType>
                <property>1024</property>
                <critMult>3</critMult>
                <weight>9.0</weight>
                <value>5.0</value>
                <text>A longspear has reach. You can strike opponents 10 feet away with it, but you can’t use it against
                    an adjacent foe. If you use a ready action to set a longspear against a charge, you deal double
                    damage on a successful hit against a charging character.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Whip</name>
                <type>5</type>
                <damage>1d2</damage>
                <damageType>3</damageType>
                <property>1154</property>
                <weight>2.0</weight>
                <value>1.0</value>
                <text>A whip deals nonlethal damage. It deals no damage to any creature with an armor bonus of +1 or
                    higher or a natural armor bonus of +3 or higher. The whip is treated as a melee weapon with 15-foot
                    reach, though you don’t threaten the area into which you can make an attack. In addition, unlike
                    most other weapons with reach, you can use it against foes anywhere within your reach (including
                    adjacent foes).
                    Using a whip provokes an attack of opportunity, just as if you had used a ranged weapon.
                    You can make trip attacks with a whip. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop
                    the whip to avoid being tripped.
                    When using a whip, you get a +2 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an opponent (including
                    the roll to keep from being disarmed if the attack fails).
                    You can use the Weapon Finesse feat to apply your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength
                    modifier to attack rolls with a whip sized for you, even though it isn’t a light weapon for you.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Sling &#38; Bullets (Cold Iron)</name>
                <type>8</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>0.5</weight>
                <value>0.01</value>
                <quantity>40</quantity>
                <text>Bullets come in a leather pouch that holds 10 bullets. A bullet that hits its target is destroyed;
                    one that misses has a 50% chance of being destroyed or lost.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Long Sword</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Quarterstaff</name>
                <slot>3</slot>
                <type>6</type>
                <damage>1d6</damage>
                <damageType>1</damageType>
                <property>64</property>
                <weight>4.0</weight>
                <text>A quarterstaff is a double weapon. You can fight with it as if fighting with two weapons, but if
                    you do, you incur all the normal attack penalties associated with fighting with two weapons, just as
                    if you were using a one-handed weapon and a light weapon. A creature wielding a quarterstaff in one
                    hand can’t use it as a double weapon0only one end of the weapon can be used in any given round.
                    The quarterstaff is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a quarterstaff
                    special options.
                </text>
            </item>
        </container>
        <container>
            <name>Scrolls</name>
            <item>
                <name>Spiderclimb</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Pyrotechnics</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>2</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Web</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>2</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Knock</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>2</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Glitterdust</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Darkness</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Color Spray</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Enlarge</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>2</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Hold Portal</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Silent Image</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Summon Monster 1</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Grease</name>
                <type>12</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Comprehend linguistics</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
        </container>
        <container>
            <name>Potions</name>
            <item>
                <name>Levitate</name>
                <type>9</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Blur</name>
                <type>9</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Glib</name>
                <type>9</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Vision</name>
                <type>9</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
        </container>
        <container>
            <name>Wands</name>
            <item>
                <name>Mage Armor</name>
                <type>14</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>4</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Shield</name>
                <type>14</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>42</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Cure Light</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Light</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>20</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Magic Missile L3</name>
                <type>14</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>7</quantity>
            </item>
        </container>
        <container>
            <name>Handy Haversack</name>
            <item>
                <name>Holy Symbol, Garl</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <value>1.0</value>
                <text>A holy symbol focuses positive energy. A cleric or paladin uses it as the focus for his spells and
                    as a tool for turning undead. Each religion has its own holy symbol.
                    Unholy Symbols: An unholy symbol is like a holy symbol except that it focuses negative energy and is
                    used by evil clerics (or by neutral clerics who want to cast evil spells or command undead).
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Alchemist’s Fire (flask)</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>1.0</weight>
                <value>20.0</value>
                <quantity>2</quantity>
                <text>You can throw a flask of alchemist’s fire as a splash weapon. Treat this attack as a ranged touch
                    attack with a range increment of 10 feet.
                    A direct hit deals 1d6 points of fire damage. Every creature within 5 feet of the point where the
                    flask hits takes 1 point of fire damage from the splash. On the round following a direct hit, the
                    target takes an additional 1d6 points of damage. If desired, the target can use a full-round action
                    to attempt to extinguish the flames before taking this additional damage. Extinguishing the flames
                    requires a DC 15 Reflex save. Rolling on the ground provides the target a +2 bonus on the save.
                    Leaping into a lake or magically extinguishing the flames automatically smothers the fire.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Antitoxin (vial)</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <value>50.0</value>
                <text>If you drink antitoxin, you get a +5 alchemical bonus on Fortitude saving throws against poison
                    for 1 hour.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Brooch</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <value>600.0</value>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Case, Map or Scroll</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>0.5</weight>
                <value>1.0</value>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Chalk</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <value>0.01</value>
                <quantity>5</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Cheese</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Cowbell</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Mirror, Small Steel</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>0.5</weight>
                <value>10.0</value>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Rations, Trail (per day)</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>1.0</weight>
                <value>0.5</value>
                <quantity>5</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Rope, Silk (50 ft.)</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>5.0</weight>
                <value>10.0</value>
                <text>This rope has 4 hit points and can be burst with a DC 24 Strength check. It is so supple that it
                    provides a +2 circumstance bonus on Use Rope checks.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Smokestick</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>0.5</weight>
                <value>20.0</value>
                <text>This alchemically treated wooden stick instantly creates thick, opaque smoke when ignited. The
                    smoke fills a 10- foot cube (treat the effect as a fog cloud spell, except that a moderate or
                    stronger wind dissipates the smoke in 1 round). The stick is consumed after 1 round, and the smoke
                    dissipates naturally.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Spellbook, Wizard’s</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>3.0</weight>
                <value>15.0</value>
                <text>A spellbook has 100 pages of parchment, and each spell takes up one page per spell level (one page
                    each for 0-level spells).
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Spell Component Pouch</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>2.0</weight>
                <value>5.0</value>
                <text>A spellcaster with a spell component pouch is assumed to have all the material components and
                    focuses needed for spellcasting, except for those components that have a specific cost, divine
                    focuses, and focuses that wouldn’t fit in a pouch.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Sunrod</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>1.0</weight>
                <value>2.0</value>
                <quantity>2</quantity>
                <text>This 1-foot-long, gold-tipped, iron rod glows brightly when struck. It clearly illuminates a
                    30-foot radius and provides shadowy illumination in a 60-foot radius. It glows for 6 hours, after
                    which the gold tip is burned out and worthless.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Tindertwig</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <value>1.0</value>
                <quantity>5</quantity>
                <text>The alchemical substance on the end of this small, wooden stick ignites when struck against a
                    rough surface. Creating a flame with a tindertwig is much faster than creating a flame with flint
                    and steel (or a magnifying glass) and tinder. Lighting a torch with a tindertwig is a standard
                    action (rather than a full-round action), and lighting any other fire with one is at least a
                    standard action.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Waterskin</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>4.0</weight>
                <value>1.0</value>
                <quantity>3</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Holy water (flask)</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>1.0</weight>
                <value>25.0</value>
                <text>Holy water damages undead creatures and evil outsiders almost as if it were acid. A flask of holy
                    water can be thrown as a splash weapon.
                    Treat this attack as a ranged touch attack with a range increment of 10 feet. A flask breaks if
                    thrown against the body of a corporeal creature, but to use it against an incorporeal creature, you
                    must open the flask and pour the holy water out onto the target. Thus, you can douse an incorporeal
                    creature with holy water only if you are adjacent to it. Doing so is a ranged touch attack that does
                    not provoke attacks of opportunity.
                    A direct hit by a flask of holy water deals 2d4 points of damage to an undead creature or an evil
                    outsider. Each such creature within 5 feet of the point where the flask hits takes 1 point of damage
                    from the splash.
                    Temples to good deities sell holy water at cost (making no profit).
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Bullets, Sling (Silver)</name>
                <type>8</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>0.5</weight>
                <value>0.01</value>
                <quantity>10</quantity>
                <text>Bullets come in a leather pouch that holds 10 bullets. A bullet that hits its target is destroyed;
                    one that misses has a 50% chance of being destroyed or lost.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Bullets, Sling (Adamantine)</name>
                <type>8</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>0.5</weight>
                <value>0.01</value>
                <text>Bullets come in a leather pouch that holds 10 bullets. A bullet that hits its target is destroyed;
                    one that misses has a 50% chance of being destroyed or lost.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Gold Pieces</name>
                <type>18</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>0.02</weight>
                <value>1892.0</value>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Flint and Steel</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <value>1.0</value>
                <text>Lighting a torch with flint and steel is a full-round action, and lighting any other fire with
                    them takes at least that long.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Crowbar</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>5.0</weight>
                <value>2.0</value>
                <text>A crowbar it grants a +2 circumstance bonus on Strength checks made for such purposes. If used in
                    combat, treat a crowbar as a one-handed improvised weapon that deals bludgeoning damage equal to
                    that of a club of its size.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Tent</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>20.0</weight>
                <value>10.0</value>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Whetstone</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>1.0</weight>
                <value>0.02</value>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Mooncalf Tentacle Scarf</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
        </container>
        <note>
            <title>Alignment</title>
            <text>Chaotic Neutral</text>
        </note>
        <monster>
            <label>Stoney</label>
            <name>Weasel</name>
            <cr>-4</cr>
            <size>2</size>
            <type>Animal</type>
            <initiative>2</initiative>
            <senses>low-light vision, scent</senses>
            <ac>14</ac>
            <touchAC>14</touchAC>
            <flatFootedAC>12</flatFootedAC>
            <acMods>+2 size, +2 Dex</acMods>
            <hpMax>2</hpMax>
            <hpCurrent>2</hpCurrent>
            <hd>1d8/2</hd>
            <fortitude>2</fortitude>
            <reflex>4</reflex>
            <will>1</will>
            <speed>20 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
            <attackMelee>Bite +4 (1d3-4)</attackMelee>
            <space>2-1/2 ft.</space>
            <reach>0 ft.</reach>
            <abilities>10,3,15,10,2,12,5,</abilities>
            <grapple>-12</grapple>
            <feats>Weapon Finesse</feats>
            <skills>Balance +10, Climb +10, Hide +11, Move Silently +8, Spot +3</skills>
            <feat>
                <name>Attach (Ex)</name>
                <text>If a weasel hits with a bite attack, it uses its powerful jaws to latch onto the opponent&#39;s
                    body and automatically deals bite damage each round it remains attached. An attached weasel loses
                    its Dexterity bonus to Armor Class and has an AC of 12. An attached weasel can be struck with a
                    weapon or grappled itself. To remove an attached weasel through grappling, the opponent must achieve
                    a pin against the creature.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Skills</name>
                <text>Weasels have a +4 racial bonus on Move Silently checks and a +8 racial bonus on Balance and Climb
                    checks. They use their Dexterity modifier for Climb checks. A weasel can always choose to take 10 on
                    a Climb check, even if rushed or threatened.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <action>
                <name>Bite</name>
                <attack>4</attack>
                <damage>1d3-4</damage>
            </action>
        </monster>
        <monster>
            <label>Myla Til</label>
            <name>Pony</name>
            <cr>-4</cr>
            <type>Animal</type>
            <initiative>1</initiative>
            <senses>low-light vision, scent</senses>
            <ac>13</ac>
            <touchAC>11</touchAC>
            <flatFootedAC>12</flatFootedAC>
            <acMods>+1 Dex, +2 natural</acMods>
            <hpMax>11</hpMax>
            <hpCurrent>11</hpCurrent>
            <hd>2d8+2</hd>
            <fortitude>4</fortitude>
            <reflex>4</reflex>
            <speed>40 ft.</speed>
            <attackMelee>2 hooves -3 (1d3*)</attackMelee>
            <space>5 ft.</space>
            <reach>5 ft.</reach>
            <abilities>10,13,13,12,2,11,4,</abilities>
            <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
            <grapple>2</grapple>
            <feats>Endurance</feats>
            <skills>Listen +5, Spot +5</skills>
            <feat>
                <name>Carrying Capacity</name>
                <text>A light load for a pony is up to 75 pounds; a medium load, 76-150 pounds; and a heavy load,
                    151-225 pounds. A pony can drag 1,125 pounds.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <action>
                <name>Hooves</name>
                <attack>-3</attack>
                <damage>1d3</damage>
            </action>
        </monster>
        <modifier>
            <type>9</type>
            <value>3</value>
        </modifier>
        <modifier>
            <type>9</type>
            <value>4</value>
            <activated>false</activated>
        </modifier>
    </character>
</pc>