<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<pc version="3">
    <character>
        <uniqueID>1047</uniqueID>
        <name>Jules</name>
        <imageData>
            <uniqueID>1049</uniqueID>
        </imageData>
        <race>
            <name>Human</name>
            <gender>Female</gender>
            <age>23</age>
            <height>5’7”</height>
            <weight>140</weight>
            <hair>Brown</hair>
            <eyes>Brown</eyes>
            <feat>
                <name>Bonus Feat</name>
                <text>1 extra feat at 1st level.</text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Skilled</name>
                <text>4 extra skill points at 1st level and 1 extra skill point at each additional level.</text>
                <modifier>
                    <type>28</type>
                    <value>1</value>
                </modifier>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Languages</name>
                <text>Common. Bonus Languages: Any (other than secret languages, such as Druidic). See the Speak
                    Language skill.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Favored Class</name>
                <text>Any. When determining whether a multiclass human takes an experience point penalty, his or her
                    highest-level class does not count.
                </text>
            </feat>
        </race>
        <class>
            <id>1111</id>
            <name>Monk</name>
            <level>8</level>
            <skills>Balance, Climb, Concentration, Craft, Diplomacy, Escape Artist, Hide, Jump, Knowledge (arcana),
                Knowledge (religion), Listen, Move Silently, Perform, Profession, Sense Motive, Spot, Swim, Tumble
            </skills>
            <skillPoints>4</skillPoints>
            <wealth>5d4</wealth>
            <baseAttack>6</baseAttack>
            <fortitude>6</fortitude>
            <reflex>6</reflex>
            <will>6</will>
            <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            <slotsCurrent>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slotsCurrent>
            <feat>
                <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                <text>Monks are proficient with club, crossbow (light or heavy), dagger, handaxe, javelin, kama,
                    nunchaku, quarterstaff, sai, shuriken, siangham, and sling.
                    Monks are not proficient with any armor or shields
                    When wearing armor, using a shield, or carrying a medium or heavy load, a monk loses her AC bonus,
                    as well as her fast movement and flurry of blows abilities.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>AC Bonus (Ex)</name>
                <text>When unarmored and unencumbered, the monk adds her Wisdom bonus (if any) to her AC. In addition, a
                    monk gains a +1 bonus to AC at 5th level. This bonus increases by 1 for every five monk levels
                    thereafter (+2 at 10th, +3 at 15th, and +4 at 20th level).
                    These bonuses to AC apply even against touch attacks or when the monk is flat-footed. She loses
                    these bonuses when she is immobilized or helpless, when she wears any armor, when she carries a
                    shield, or when she carries a medium or heavy load.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Flurry of Blows (Ex)</name>
                <text>When unarmored, a monk may strike with a flurry of blows at the expense of accuracy. When doing
                    so, she may make one extra attack in a round at her highest base attack bonus, but this attack takes
                    a -2 penalty, as does each other attack made that round. The resulting modified base attack bonuses
                    are shown in the Flurry of Blows Attack Bonus column on Table: The Monk. This penalty applies for 1
                    round, so it also affects attacks of opportunity the monk might make before her next action. When a
                    monk reaches 5th level, the penalty lessens to -1, and at 9th level it disappears. A monk must use a
                    full attack action to strike with a flurry of blows.
                    When using flurry of blows, a monk may attack only with unarmed strikes or with special monk weapons
                    (kama, nunchaku, quarterstaff, sai, shuriken, and siangham). She may attack with unarmed strikes and
                    special monk weapons interchangeably as desired. When using weapons as part of a flurry of blows, a
                    monk applies her Strength bonus (not Str bonus × 1½ or ×½) to her damage rolls for all successful
                    attacks, whether she wields a weapon in one or both hands. The monk can’t use any weapon other than
                    a special monk weapon as part of a flurry of blows.
                    In the case of the quarterstaff, each end counts as a separate weapon for the purpose of using the
                    flurry of blows ability. Even though the quarterstaff requires two hands to use, a monk may still
                    intersperse unarmed strikes with quarterstaff strikes, assuming that she has enough attacks in her
                    flurry of blows routine to do so.
                    Greater Flurry. When a monk reaches 11th level, her flurry of blows ability improves. In addition to
                    the standard single extra attack she gets from flurry of blows, she gets a second extra attack at
                    her full base attack bonus.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
                <text>At 1st level, a monk gains Improved Unarmed Strike as a bonus feat. A monk’s attacks may be with
                    either fist interchangeably or even from elbows, knees, and feet. This means that a monk may even
                    make unarmed strikes with her hands full. There is no such thing as an off-hand attack for a monk
                    striking unarmed. A monk may thus apply her full Strength bonus on damage rolls for all her unarmed
                    strikes.
                    Usually a monk’s unarmed strikes deal lethal damage, but she can choose to deal nonlethal damage
                    instead with no penalty on her attack roll. She has the same choice to deal lethal or nonlethal
                    damage while grappling.
                    A monk’s unarmed strike is treated both as a manufactured weapon and a natural weapon for the
                    purpose of spells and effects that enhance or improve either manufactured weapons or natural
                    weapons.
                    A monk also deals more damage with her unarmed strikes than a normal person would, as shown on
                    Table: The Monk. The unarmed damage on Table: The Monk is for Medium monks. A Small monk deals less
                    damage than the amount given there with her unarmed attacks, while a Large monk deals more damage;
                    see Table: Small or Large Monk Unarmed Damage.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Bonus Feat</name>
                <text>At 1st level, a monk may select either Improved Grapple or Stunning Fist as a bonus feat. At 2nd
                    level, she may select either Combat Reflexes or Deflect Arrows as a bonus feat. At 6th level, she
                    may select either Improved Disarm or Improved Trip as a bonus feat. A monk need not have any of the
                    prerequisites normally required for these feats to select them.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Evasion (Ex)</name>
                <text>At 2nd level or higher if a monk makes a successful Reflex saving throw against an attack that
                    normally deals half damage on a successful save, she instead takes no damage. Evasion can be used
                    only if a monk is wearing light armor or no armor. A helpless monk does not gain the benefit of
                    evasion.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Fast Movement (Ex)</name>
                <text>At 3rd level, a monk gains an enhancement bonus to her speed, as shown on Table: The Monk. A monk
                    in armor or carrying a medium or heavy load loses this extra speed.
                </text>
                <modifier>
                    <type>19</type>
                    <value>20</value>
                </modifier>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Still Mind (Ex)</name>
                <text>A monk of 3rd level or higher gains a +2 bonus on saving throws against spells and effects from
                    the school of enchantment.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Ki Strike (Su)</name>
                <text>At 4th level, a monk’s unarmed attacks are empowered with ki. Her unarmed attacks are treated as
                    magic weapons for the purpose of dealing damage to creatures with damage reduction. Ki strike
                    improves with the character’s monk level. At 10th level, her unarmed attacks are also treated as
                    lawful weapons for the purpose of dealing damage to creatures with damage reduction. At 16th level,
                    her unarmed attacks are treated as adamantine weapons for the purpose of dealing damage to creatures
                    with damage reduction and bypassing hardness.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Slow Fall (Ex)</name>
                <text>At 4th level or higher, a monk within arm’s reach of a wall can use it to slow her descent. When
                    first using this ability, she takes damage as if the fall were 20 feet shorter than it actually is.
                    The monk’s ability to slow her fall (that is, to reduce the effective distance of the fall when next
                    to a wall) improves with her monk level until at 20th level she can use a nearby wall to slow her
                    descent and fall any distance without harm.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Purity of Body (Ex)</name>
                <text>At 5th level, a monk gains immunity to all diseases except for supernatural and magical
                    diseases.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Wholeness of Body (Su)</name>
                <text>At 7th level or higher, a monk can heal her own wounds. She can heal a number of hit points of
                    damage equal to twice her current monk level each day, and she can spread this healing out among
                    several uses.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <autolevel>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>2</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                    <text>Monks are proficient with club, crossbow (light or heavy), dagger, handaxe, javelin, kama,
                        nunchaku, quarterstaff, sai, shuriken, siangham, and sling.
                        Monks are not proficient with any armor or shields
                        When wearing armor, using a shield, or carrying a medium or heavy load, a monk loses her AC
                        bonus, as well as her fast movement and flurry of blows abilities.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>AC Bonus (Ex)</name>
                    <text>When unarmored and unencumbered, the monk adds her Wisdom bonus (if any) to her AC. In
                        addition, a monk gains a +1 bonus to AC at 5th level. This bonus increases by 1 for every five
                        monk levels thereafter (+2 at 10th, +3 at 15th, and +4 at 20th level).
                        These bonuses to AC apply even against touch attacks or when the monk is flat-footed. She loses
                        these bonuses when she is immobilized or helpless, when she wears any armor, when she carries a
                        shield, or when she carries a medium or heavy load.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Flurry of Blows (Ex)</name>
                    <text>When unarmored, a monk may strike with a flurry of blows at the expense of accuracy. When
                        doing so, she may make one extra attack in a round at her highest base attack bonus, but this
                        attack takes a -2 penalty, as does each other attack made that round. The resulting modified
                        base attack bonuses are shown in the Flurry of Blows Attack Bonus column on Table: The Monk.
                        This penalty applies for 1 round, so it also affects attacks of opportunity the monk might make
                        before her next action. When a monk reaches 5th level, the penalty lessens to -1, and at 9th
                        level it disappears. A monk must use a full attack action to strike with a flurry of blows.
                        When using flurry of blows, a monk may attack only with unarmed strikes or with special monk
                        weapons (kama, nunchaku, quarterstaff, sai, shuriken, and siangham). She may attack with unarmed
                        strikes and special monk weapons interchangeably as desired. When using weapons as part of a
                        flurry of blows, a monk applies her Strength bonus (not Str bonus × 1½ or ×½) to her damage
                        rolls for all successful attacks, whether she wields a weapon in one or both hands. The monk
                        can’t use any weapon other than a special monk weapon as part of a flurry of blows.
                        In the case of the quarterstaff, each end counts as a separate weapon for the purpose of using
                        the flurry of blows ability. Even though the quarterstaff requires two hands to use, a monk may
                        still intersperse unarmed strikes with quarterstaff strikes, assuming that she has enough
                        attacks in her flurry of blows routine to do so.
                        Greater Flurry. When a monk reaches 11th level, her flurry of blows ability improves. In
                        addition to the standard single extra attack she gets from flurry of blows, she gets a second
                        extra attack at her full base attack bonus.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
                    <text>At 1st level, a monk gains Improved Unarmed Strike as a bonus feat. A monk’s attacks may be
                        with either fist interchangeably or even from elbows, knees, and feet. This means that a monk
                        may even make unarmed strikes with her hands full. There is no such thing as an off-hand attack
                        for a monk striking unarmed. A monk may thus apply her full Strength bonus on damage rolls for
                        all her unarmed strikes.
                        Usually a monk’s unarmed strikes deal lethal damage, but she can choose to deal nonlethal damage
                        instead with no penalty on her attack roll. She has the same choice to deal lethal or nonlethal
                        damage while grappling.
                        A monk’s unarmed strike is treated both as a manufactured weapon and a natural weapon for the
                        purpose of spells and effects that enhance or improve either manufactured weapons or natural
                        weapons.
                        A monk also deals more damage with her unarmed strikes than a normal person would, as shown on
                        Table: The Monk. The unarmed damage on Table: The Monk is for Medium monks. A Small monk deals
                        less damage than the amount given there with her unarmed attacks, while a Large monk deals more
                        damage; see Table: Small or Large Monk Unarmed Damage.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Feat</name>
                    <text>At 1st level, a monk may select either Improved Grapple or Stunning Fist as a bonus feat. At
                        2nd level, she may select either Combat Reflexes or Deflect Arrows as a bonus feat. At 6th
                        level, she may select either Improved Disarm or Improved Trip as a bonus feat. A monk need not
                        have any of the prerequisites normally required for these feats to select them.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>2</level>
                <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Evasion (Ex)</name>
                    <text>At 2nd level or higher if a monk makes a successful Reflex saving throw against an attack that
                        normally deals half damage on a successful save, she instead takes no damage. Evasion can be
                        used only if a monk is wearing light armor or no armor. A helpless monk does not gain the
                        benefit of evasion.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>3</level>
                <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Fast Movement (Ex)</name>
                    <text>At 3rd level, a monk gains an enhancement bonus to her speed, as shown on Table: The Monk. A
                        monk in armor or carrying a medium or heavy load loses this extra speed.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Still Mind (Ex)</name>
                    <text>A monk of 3rd level or higher gains a +2 bonus on saving throws against spells and effects
                        from the school of enchantment.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>4</level>
                <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>4</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Ki Strike (Su)</name>
                    <text>At 4th level, a monk’s unarmed attacks are empowered with ki. Her unarmed attacks are treated
                        as magic weapons for the purpose of dealing damage to creatures with damage reduction. Ki strike
                        improves with the character’s monk level. At 10th level, her unarmed attacks are also treated as
                        lawful weapons for the purpose of dealing damage to creatures with damage reduction. At 16th
                        level, her unarmed attacks are treated as adamantine weapons for the purpose of dealing damage
                        to creatures with damage reduction and bypassing hardness.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Slow Fall (Ex)</name>
                    <text>At 4th level or higher, a monk within arm’s reach of a wall can use it to slow her descent.
                        When first using this ability, she takes damage as if the fall were 20 feet shorter than it
                        actually is. The monk’s ability to slow her fall (that is, to reduce the effective distance of
                        the fall when next to a wall) improves with her monk level until at 20th level she can use a
                        nearby wall to slow her descent and fall any distance without harm.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>5</level>
                <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>4</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Purity of Body (Ex)</name>
                    <text>At 5th level, a monk gains immunity to all diseases except for supernatural and magical
                        diseases.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>6</level>
                <baseAttack>4</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>5</reflex>
                <will>5</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>7</level>
                <baseAttack>5</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>5</reflex>
                <will>5</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Wholeness of Body (Su)</name>
                    <text>At 7th level or higher, a monk can heal her own wounds. She can heal a number of hit points of
                        damage equal to twice her current monk level each day, and she can spread this healing out among
                        several uses.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>8</level>
                <baseAttack>6</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>6</reflex>
                <will>6</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>9</level>
                <baseAttack>6</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>6</reflex>
                <will>6</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Improved Evasion (Ex)</name>
                    <text>At 9th level, a monk’s evasion ability improves. She still takes no damage on a successful
                        Reflex saving throw against attacks, but henceforth she takes only half damage on a failed save.
                        A helpless monk does not gain the benefit of improved evasion.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>10</level>
                <baseAttack>7</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>7</fortitude>
                <reflex>7</reflex>
                <will>7</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>11</level>
                <baseAttack>8</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>7</fortitude>
                <reflex>7</reflex>
                <will>7</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Diamond Body (Su)</name>
                    <text>At 11th level, a monk gains immunity to poisons of all kinds.</text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>12</level>
                <baseAttack>9</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>8</fortitude>
                <reflex>8</reflex>
                <will>8</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Abundant Step (Su)</name>
                    <text>At 12th level or higher, a monk can slip magically between spaces, as if using the spell
                        dimension door, once per day. Her caster level for this effect is one-half her monk level
                        (rounded down).
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>13</level>
                <baseAttack>9</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>8</fortitude>
                <reflex>8</reflex>
                <will>8</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Diamond Soul (Ex)</name>
                    <text>At 13th level, a monk gains spell resistance equal to her current monk level + 10. In order to
                        affect the monk with a spell, a spellcaster must get a result on a caster level check (1d20 +
                        caster level) that equals or exceeds the monk’s spell resistance.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>14</level>
                <baseAttack>10</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>9</fortitude>
                <reflex>9</reflex>
                <will>9</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>15</level>
                <baseAttack>11</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>9</fortitude>
                <reflex>9</reflex>
                <will>9</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Quivering Palm (Su)</name>
                    <text>Starting at 15th level, a monk can set up vibrations within the body of another creature that
                        can thereafter be fatal if the monk so desires. She can use this quivering palm attack once a
                        week, and she must announce her intent before making her attack roll. Constructs, oozes, plants,
                        undead, incorporeal creatures, and creatures immune to critical hits cannot be affected.
                        Otherwise, if the monk strikes successfully and the target takes damage from the blow, the
                        quivering palm attack succeeds. Thereafter the monk can try to slay the victim at any later
                        time, as long as the attempt is made within a number of days equal to her monk level. To make
                        such an attempt, the monk merely wills the target to die (a free action), and unless the target
                        makes a Fortitude saving throw (DC 10 + ½ the monk’s level + the monk’s Wis modifier), it dies.
                        If the saving throw is successful, the target is no longer in danger from that particular
                        quivering palm attack, but it may still be affected by another one at a later time.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>16</level>
                <baseAttack>12</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>10</fortitude>
                <reflex>10</reflex>
                <will>10</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>17</level>
                <baseAttack>12</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>10</fortitude>
                <reflex>10</reflex>
                <will>10</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Timeless Body (Ex)</name>
                    <text>Upon attaining 17th level, a monk no longer takes penalties to her ability scores for aging
                        and cannot be magically aged. Any such penalties that she has already taken, however, remain in
                        place. Bonuses still accrue, and the monk still dies of old age when her time is up.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Tongue of the Sun and Moon (Ex)</name>
                    <text>A monk of 17th level or higher can speak with any living creature.</text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>18</level>
                <baseAttack>13</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>11</fortitude>
                <reflex>11</reflex>
                <will>11</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>19</level>
                <baseAttack>14</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>11</fortitude>
                <reflex>11</reflex>
                <will>11</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Empty Body (Su)</name>
                    <text>At 19th level, a monk gains the ability to assume an ethereal state for 1 round per monk level
                        per day, as though using the spell etherealness. She may go ethereal on a number of different
                        occasions during any single day, as long as the total number of rounds spent in an ethereal
                        state does not exceed her monk level.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>20</level>
                <baseAttack>15</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>12</fortitude>
                <reflex>12</reflex>
                <will>12</will>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Perfect Self</name>
                    <text>At 20th level, a monk becomes a magical creature. She is forevermore treated as an outsider
                        rather than as a humanoid (or whatever the monk’s creature type was) for the purpose of spells
                        and magical effects. Additionally, the monk gains damage reduction 10/magic, which allows her to
                        ignore the first 10 points of damage from any attack made by a nonmagical weapon or by any
                        natural attack made by a creature that doesn’t have similar damage reduction. Unlike other
                        outsiders, the monk can still be brought back from the dead as if she were a member of her
                        previous creature type.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <skills>Balance, Climb, Concentration, Craft, Diplomacy, Escape Artist, Hide, Jump, Knowledge (arcana),
                Knowledge (religion), Listen, Move Silently, Perform, Profession, Sense Motive, Spot, Swim, Tumble
            </skills>
            <spellAbility>6</spellAbility>
        </class>
        <class>
            <id>1098</id>
            <name>Wizard</name>
            <hd>0</hd>
            <skills>Concentration, Craft, Decipher Script, Knowledge, Profession, Spellcraft</skills>
            <wealth>3d4x10</wealth>
            <will>2</will>
            <slots>3,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            <slotsCurrent>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slotsCurrent>
            <feat>
                <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                <text>Wizards are proficient with the club, dagger, heavy crossbow, light crossbow, and quarterstaff,
                    but not with any type of armor or shield. Armor of any type interferes with a wizard’s movements,
                    which can cause her spells with somatic components to fail.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Spells</name>
                <text>A wizard casts arcane spells which are drawn from the sorcerer/wizard spell list. A wizard must
                    choose and prepare her spells ahead of time (see below).
                    To learn, prepare, or cast a spell, the wizard must have an Intelligence score equal to at least 10
                    + the spell level. The Difficulty Class for a saving throw against a wizard’s spell is 10 + the
                    spell level + the wizard’s Intelligence modifier.
                    Like other spellcasters, a wizard can cast only a certain number of spells of each spell level per
                    day. Her base daily spell allotment is given on Table: The Wizard. In addition, she receives bonus
                    spells per day if she has a high Intelligence score.
                    Unlike a bard or sorcerer, a wizard may know any number of spells. She must choose and prepare her
                    spells ahead of time by getting a good night’s sleep and spending 1 hour studying her spellbook.
                    While studying, the wizard decides which spells to prepare.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <feat>
                <name>Spellbooks</name>
                <text>A wizard must study her spellbook each day to prepare her spells. She cannot prepare any spell not
                    recorded in her spellbook, except for read magic, which all wizards can prepare from memory.
                    A wizard begins play with a spellbook containing all 0-level wizard spells (except those from her
                    prohibited school or schools, if any; see School Specialization, below) plus three 1st-level spells
                    of your choice. For each point of Intelligence bonus the wizard has, the spellbook holds one
                    additional 1st-level spell of your choice. At each new wizard level, she gains two new spells of any
                    spell level or levels that she can cast (based on her new wizard level) for her spellbook. At any
                    time, a wizard can also add spells found in other wizards’ spellbooks to her own.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <autolevel>
                <will>2</will>
                <slots>3,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Weapon and Armor Proficiency</name>
                    <text>Wizards are proficient with the club, dagger, heavy crossbow, light crossbow, and
                        quarterstaff, but not with any type of armor or shield. Armor of any type interferes with a
                        wizard’s movements, which can cause her spells with somatic components to fail.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Spells</name>
                    <text>A wizard casts arcane spells which are drawn from the sorcerer/wizard spell list. A wizard
                        must choose and prepare her spells ahead of time (see below).
                        To learn, prepare, or cast a spell, the wizard must have an Intelligence score equal to at least
                        10 + the spell level. The Difficulty Class for a saving throw against a wizard’s spell is 10 +
                        the spell level + the wizard’s Intelligence modifier.
                        Like other spellcasters, a wizard can cast only a certain number of spells of each spell level
                        per day. Her base daily spell allotment is given on Table: The Wizard. In addition, she receives
                        bonus spells per day if she has a high Intelligence score.
                        Unlike a bard or sorcerer, a wizard may know any number of spells. She must choose and prepare
                        her spells ahead of time by getting a good night’s sleep and spending 1 hour studying her
                        spellbook. While studying, the wizard decides which spells to prepare.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Spellbooks</name>
                    <text>A wizard must study her spellbook each day to prepare her spells. She cannot prepare any spell
                        not recorded in her spellbook, except for read magic, which all wizards can prepare from memory.
                        A wizard begins play with a spellbook containing all 0-level wizard spells (except those from
                        her prohibited school or schools, if any; see School Specialization, below) plus three 1st-level
                        spells of your choice. For each point of Intelligence bonus the wizard has, the spellbook holds
                        one additional 1st-level spell of your choice. At each new wizard level, she gains two new
                        spells of any spell level or levels that she can cast (based on her new wizard level) for her
                        spellbook. At any time, a wizard can also add spells found in other wizards’ spellbooks to her
                        own.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Languages</name>
                    <text>A wizard may substitute Draconic for one of the bonus languages available to the character
                        because of her race.
                    </text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Familiar</name>
                    <text>A wizard can obtain a familiar in exactly the same manner as a sorcerer can.</text>
                </feat>
                <feat>
                    <name>Scribe Scroll</name>
                    <text>At 1st level, a wizard gains Scribe Scroll as a bonus feat.</text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>2</level>
                <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>4,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>3</level>
                <baseAttack>1</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>3</will>
                <slots>4,2,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>4</level>
                <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>4,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>5</level>
                <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>1</fortitude>
                <reflex>1</reflex>
                <will>4</will>
                <slots>4,3,2,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Feats</name>
                    <text>At 5th level, a wizard gains a bonus feat. At each such opportunity, she can choose a
                        metamagic feat, an item creation feat, or Spell Mastery. The wizard must still meet all
                        prerequisites for a bonus feat, including caster level minimums.
                        These bonus feats are in addition to the feat that a character of any class gets from advancing
                        levels. The wizard is not limited to the categories of item creation feats, metamagic feats, or
                        Spell Mastery when choosing these feats.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>6</level>
                <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>5</will>
                <slots>4,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>7</level>
                <baseAttack>3</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>5</will>
                <slots>4,4,3,2,1,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>8</level>
                <baseAttack>4</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>2</fortitude>
                <reflex>2</reflex>
                <will>6</will>
                <slots>4,4,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>9</level>
                <baseAttack>4</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>6</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,3,2,1,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>10</level>
                <baseAttack>5</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>7</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,3,3,2,0,0,0,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Feats</name>
                    <text>At 10th, a wizard gains a bonus feat. At each such opportunity, she can choose a metamagic
                        feat, an item creation feat, or Spell Mastery. The wizard must still meet all prerequisites for
                        a bonus feat, including caster level minimums.
                        These bonus feats are in addition to the feat that a character of any class gets from advancing
                        levels. The wizard is not limited to the categories of item creation feats, metamagic feats, or
                        Spell Mastery when choosing these feats.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>11</level>
                <baseAttack>5</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>3</fortitude>
                <reflex>3</reflex>
                <will>7</will>
                <slots>4,6,4,4,3,2,1,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>12</level>
                <baseAttack>6</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>4</reflex>
                <will>8</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,3,3,2,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>13</level>
                <baseAttack>6</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>4</reflex>
                <will>8</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,3,2,1,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>14</level>
                <baseAttack>7</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>4</fortitude>
                <reflex>4</reflex>
                <will>9</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,3,3,2,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>15</level>
                <baseAttack>7</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>5</reflex>
                <will>9</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,3,2,1,0,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Feats</name>
                    <text>At 15th, a wizard gains a bonus feat. At each such opportunity, she can choose a metamagic
                        feat, an item creation feat, or Spell Mastery. The wizard must still meet all prerequisites for
                        a bonus feat, including caster level minimums.
                        These bonus feats are in addition to the feat that a character of any class gets from advancing
                        levels. The wizard is not limited to the categories of item creation feats, metamagic feats, or
                        Spell Mastery when choosing these feats.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>16</level>
                <baseAttack>8</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>5</reflex>
                <will>10</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,3,3,2,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>17</level>
                <baseAttack>8</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>5</fortitude>
                <reflex>5</reflex>
                <will>10</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,4,3,2,1,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>18</level>
                <baseAttack>9</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>6</reflex>
                <will>11</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,4,3,3,2,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>19</level>
                <baseAttack>9</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>6</reflex>
                <will>11</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,4,4,3,3,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>20</level>
                <baseAttack>10</baseAttack>
                <fortitude>6</fortitude>
                <reflex>6</reflex>
                <will>12</will>
                <slots>4,4,4,4,4,4,4,4,4,4,</slots>
                <feat>
                    <name>Bonus Feats</name>
                    <text>At 20th level, a wizard gains a bonus feat. At each such opportunity, she can choose a
                        metamagic feat, an item creation feat, or Spell Mastery. The wizard must still meet all
                        prerequisites for a bonus feat, including caster level minimums.
                        These bonus feats are in addition to the feat that a character of any class gets from advancing
                        levels. The wizard is not limited to the categories of item creation feats, metamagic feats, or
                        Spell Mastery when choosing these feats.
                    </text>
                </feat>
            </autolevel>
            <skills>Concentration, Craft, Decipher Script, Knowledge, Profession, Spellcraft</skills>
            <spellAbility>4</spellAbility>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Shield</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>1</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Personal</range>
                <target>You</target>
                <duration>1 min./level (D)</duration>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Shield creates an invisible, tower shield-sized mobile disk of force that hovers in front of you.
                    It negates magic missile attacks directed at you. The disk also provides a +4 shield bonus to AC.
                    This bonus applies against incorporeal touch attacks, since it is a force effect. The shield has no
                    armor check penalty or arcane spell failure chance. Unlike with a normal tower shield, you can’t use
                    the shield spell for cover.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Flare</name>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>Burst of light</effect>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Fortitude negates</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>This cantrip creates a burst of light. If you cause the light to burst directly in front of a
                    single creature, that creature is dazzled for 1 minute unless it makes a successful Fortitude save.
                    Sightless creatures, as well as creatures already dazzled, are not affected by flare.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Detect Magic</name>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>60 ft.</range>
                <area>Cone-shaped emanation</area>
                <duration>Concentration, up to 1 min./level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You detect magical auras. The amount of information revealed depends on how long you study a
                    particular area or subject.
                    1st Round: Presence or absence of magical auras.
                    2nd Round: Number of different magical auras and the power of the most potent aura.
                    3rd Round: The strength and location of each aura. If the items or creatures bearing the auras are
                    in line of sight, you can make Spellcraft skill checks to determine the school of magic involved in
                    each. (Make one check per aura; DC 15 + spell level, or 15 + half caster level for a nonspell
                    effect.)
                    Magical areas, multiple types of magic, or strong local magical emanations may distort or conceal
                    weaker auras.
                    Aura Strength: An aura’s power depends on a spell’s functioning spell level or an item’s caster
                    level. If an aura falls into more than one category, detect magic indicates the stronger of the two.
                    Lingering Aura: A magical aura lingers after its original source dissipates (in the case of a spell)
                    or is destroyed (in the case of a magic item). If detect magic is cast and directed at such a
                    location, the spell indicates an aura strength of dim (even weaker than a faint aura). How long the
                    aura lingers at this dim level depends on its original power:
                    Outsiders and elementals are not magical in themselves, but if they are summoned, the conjuration
                    spell registers.
                    Each round, you can turn to detect magic in a new area. The spell can penetrate barriers, but 1 foot
                    of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead, or 3 feet of wood or dirt blocks it.
                    Detect magic can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Shocking Grasp</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Creature or object touched</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>Your successful melee touch attack deals 1d6 points of electricity damage per caster level
                    (maximum 5d6). When delivering the jolt, you gain a +3 bonus on attack rolls if the opponent is
                    wearing metal armor (or made out of metal, carrying a lot of metal, or the like).
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>2</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Acid Splash</name>
                <school>2</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>One missile of acid</effect>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You fire a small orb of acid at the target. You must succeed on a ranged touch attack to hit your
                    target. The orb deals 1d3 points of acid damage.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Read Magic</name>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, S, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Personal</range>
                <target>You</target>
                <duration>10 min./level</duration>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>By means of read magic, you can decipher magical inscriptions on objects—books, scrolls, weapons,
                    and the like—that would otherwise be unintelligible. This deciphering does not normally invoke the
                    magic contained in the writing, although it may do so in the case of a cursed scroll. Furthermore,
                    once the spell is cast and you have read the magical inscription, you are thereafter able to read
                    that particular writing without recourse to the use of read magic. You can read at the rate of one
                    page (250 words) per minute. The spell allows you to identify a glyph of warding with a DC 13
                    Spellcraft check, a greater glyph of warding with a DC 16 Spellcraft check, or any symbol spell with
                    a Spellcraft check (DC 10 + spell level).
                    Read magic can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                    Focus: A clear crystal or mineral prism.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Paladin</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Ranger</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Disrupt Undead</name>
                <school>7</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>Ray</effect>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>You direct a ray of positive energy. You must make a ranged touch attack to hit, and if the ray
                    hits an undead creature, it deals 1d6 points of damage to it.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Ghost Sound</name>
                <school>6</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>Illusory sounds</effect>
                <duration>1 round/level (D)</duration>
                <save>Will disbelief (if interacted with)</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Ghost sound allows you to create a volume of sound that rises, recedes, approaches, or remains at
                    a fixed place. You choose what type of sound ghost sound creates when casting it and cannot
                    thereafter change the sound’s basic character.
                    The volume of sound created depends on your level. You can produce as much noise as four normal
                    humans per caster level (maximum twenty humans). Thus, talking, singing, shouting, walking,
                    marching, or running sounds can be created. The noise a ghost sound spell produces can be virtually
                    any type of sound within the volume limit. A horde of rats running and squeaking is about the same
                    volume as eight humans running and shouting. A roaring lion is equal to the noise from sixteen
                    humans, while a roaring dire tiger is equal to the noise from twenty humans.
                    Ghost sound can enhance the effectiveness of a silent image spell.
                    Ghost sound can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                    Material Component: A bit of wool or a small lump of wax.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Detect Poison</name>
                <school>3</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One creature, one object, or a 5-ft. cube</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You determine whether a creature, object, or area has been poisoned or is poisonous. You can
                    determine the exact type of poison with a DC 20 Wisdom check. A character with the Craft (alchemy)
                    skill may try a DC 20 Craft (alchemy) check if the Wisdom check fails, or may try the Craft
                    (alchemy) check prior to the Wisdom check.
                    The spell can penetrate barriers, but 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead,
                    or 3 feet of wood or dirt blocks it.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Paladin</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Ranger</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Chill Touch</name>
                <level>1</level>
                <school>7</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Creature or creatures touched (up to one/level)</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Fortitude partial or Will negates; see text</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>A touch from your hand, which glows with blue energy, disrupts the life force of living creatures.
                    Each touch channels negative energy that deals 1d6 points of damage. The touched creature also takes
                    1 point of Strength damage unless it makes a successful Fortitude saving throw. You can use this
                    melee touch attack up to one time per level.
                    An undead creature you touch takes no damage of either sort, but it must make a successful Will
                    saving throw or flee as if panicked for 1d4 rounds +1 round per caster level.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Message</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <target>One creature/level</target>
                <duration>10 min./level</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You can whisper messages and receive whispered replies with little chance of being overheard. You
                    point your finger at each creature you want to receive the message. When you whisper, the whispered
                    message is audible to all targeted creatures within range. Magical silence, 1 foot of stone, 1 inch
                    of common metal (or a thin sheet of lead), or 3 feet of wood or dirt blocks the spell. The message
                    does not have to travel in a straight line. It can circumvent a barrier if there is an open path
                    between you and the subject, and the path’s entire length lies within the spell’s range. The
                    creatures that receive the message can whisper a reply that you hear. The spell transmits sound, not
                    meaning. It doesn’t transcend language barriers.
                    Note: To speak a message, you must mouth the words and whisper, possibly allowing observers the
                    opportunity to read your lips.
                    Focus: A short piece of copper wire.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Ray of Frost</name>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <effect>Ray</effect>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>A ray of freezing air and ice projects from your pointing finger. You must succeed on a ranged
                    touch attack with the ray to deal damage to a target. The ray deals 1d3 points of cold damage.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <prepared>1</prepared>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Dancing Lights</name>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Medium (100 ft. + 10 ft./level)</range>
                <effect>Up to four lights, all within a 10- ft.-radius area</effect>
                <duration>1 minute (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Depending on the version selected, you create up to four lights that resemble lanterns or torches
                    (and cast that amount of light), or up to four glowing spheres of light (which look like
                    will-o’-wisps), or one faintly glowing, vaguely humanoid shape. The dancing lights must stay within
                    a 10-foot-radius area in relation to each other but otherwise move as you desire (no concentration
                    required): forward or back, up or down, straight or turning corners, or the like. The lights can
                    move up to 100 feet per round. A light winks out if the distance between you and it exceeds the
                    spell’s range.
                    Dancing lights can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Light</name>
                <school>5</school>
                <components>V, M/DF</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Object touched</target>
                <duration>10 min./level (D)</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell causes an object to glow like a torch, shedding bright light in a 20-foot radius (and
                    dim light for an additional 20 feet) from the point you touch. The effect is immobile, but it can be
                    cast on a movable object. Light taken into an area of magical darkness does not function.
                    A light spell (one with the light descriptor) counters and dispels a darkness spell (one with the
                    darkness descriptor) of an equal or lower level.
                    Arcane Material Component: A firefly or a piece of phosphorescent moss.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Prestidigitation</name>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>10 ft.</range>
                <target>See text</target>
                <duration>1 hour</duration>
                <save>See text</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>Prestidigitations are minor tricks that novice spellcasters use for practice. Once cast, a
                    prestidigitation spell enables you to perform simple magical effects for 1 hour. The effects are
                    minor and have severe limitations. A prestidigitation can slowly lift 1 pound of material. It can
                    color, clean, or soil items in a 1-foot cube each round. It can chill, warm, or flavor 1 pound of
                    nonliving material. It cannot deal damage or affect the concentration of spellcasters.
                    Prestidigitation can create small objects, but they look crude and artificial. The materials created
                    by a prestidigitation spell are extremely fragile, and they cannot be used as tools, weapons, or
                    spell components. Finally, a prestidigitation lacks the power to duplicate any other spell effects.
                    Any actual change to an object (beyond just moving, cleaning, or soiling it) persists only 1 hour.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Arcane Mark</name>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>0 ft.</range>
                <effect>One personal rune or mark, all of which must fit within 1 sq. ft.</effect>
                <duration>Permanent</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>This spell allows you to inscribe your personal rune or mark, which can consist of no more than
                    six characters. The writing can be visible or invisible. An arcane mark spell enables you to etch
                    the rune upon any substance without harm to the material upon which it is placed. If an invisible
                    mark is made, a detect magic spell causes it to glow and be visible, though not necessarily
                    understandable.
                    See invisibility, true seeing, a gem of seeing, or a robe of eyes likewise allows the user to see an
                    invisible arcane mark. A read magic spell reveals the words, if any. The mark cannot be dispelled,
                    but it can be removed by the caster or by an erase spell.
                    If an arcane mark is placed on a living being, normal wear gradually causes the effect to fade in
                    about a month.
                    Arcane mark must be cast on an object prior to casting instant summons on the same object (see that
                    spell description for details).
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Touch of Fatigue</name>
                <school>7</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Creature touched</target>
                <duration>1 round/level</duration>
                <save>Fortitude negates</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>You channel negative energy through your touch, fatiguing the target. You must succeed on a touch
                    attack to strike a target.
                    The subject is immediately fatigued for the spell’s duration.
                    This spell has no effect on a creature that is already fatigued. Unlike with normal fatigue, the
                    effect ends as soon as the spell’s duration expires.
                    Material Component: A drop of sweat.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Open/Close</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S, F</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>Object weighing up to 30 lb. or portal that can be opened or closed</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Will negates (object)</save>
                <sr>Yes (object)</sr>
                <text>You can open or close (your choice) a door, chest, box, window, bag, pouch, bottle, barrel, or
                    other container. If anything resists this activity (such as a bar on a door or a lock on a chest),
                    the spell fails. In addition, the spell can only open and close things weighing 30 pounds or less.
                    Thus, doors, chests, and similar objects sized for enormous creatures may be beyond this spell’s
                    ability to affect.
                    Focus: A brass key.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Daze</name>
                <school>4</school>
                <components>V, S, M</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One humanoid creature of 4 HD or less</target>
                <duration>1 round</duration>
                <save>Will negates</save>
                <sr>Yes</sr>
                <text>This enchantment clouds the mind of a humanoid creature with 4 or fewer Hit Dice so that it takes
                    no actions. Humanoids of 5 or more HD are not affected. A dazed subject is not stunned, so attackers
                    get no special advantage against it.
                    Material Component: A pinch of wool or similar substance.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Mage Hand</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One nonmagical, unattended object weighing up to 5 lb.</target>
                <duration>Concentration</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You point your finger at an object and can lift it and move it at will from a distance. As a move
                    action, you can propel the object as far as 15 feet in any direction, though the spell ends if the
                    distance between you and the object ever exceeds the spell’s range.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Resistance</name>
                <school>1</school>
                <components>V, S, M/DF</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Touch</range>
                <target>Creature touched</target>
                <duration>1 minute</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless)</save>
                <sr>Yes (harmless)</sr>
                <text>You imbue the subject with magical energy that protects it from harm, granting it a +1 resistance
                    bonus on saves.
                    Resistance can be made permanent with a permanency spell.
                    Arcane Material Component: A miniature cloak.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Paladin</name>
                    <level>1</level>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Mending</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>10 ft.</range>
                <target>One object of up to 1 lb.</target>
                <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
                <save>Will negates (harmless, object)</save>
                <sr>Yes (harmless, object)</sr>
                <text>Mending repairs small breaks or tears in objects (but not warps, such as might be caused by a warp
                    wood spell). It will weld broken metallic objects such as a ring, a chain link, a medallion, or a
                    slender dagger, providing but one break exists.
                    Ceramic or wooden objects with multiple breaks can be invisibly rejoined to be as strong as new. A
                    hole in a leather sack or a wineskin is completely healed over by mending. The spell can repair a
                    magic item, but the item’s magical abilities are not restored. The spell cannot mend broken magic
                    rods, staffs, or wands, nor does it affect creatures (including constructs).
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Cleric</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Druid</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
            <spell>
                <src>1</src>
                <name>Mage Hand</name>
                <school>8</school>
                <components>V, S</components>
                <time>1 standard action</time>
                <range>Close (25 ft. + 5 ft./2 levels)</range>
                <target>One nonmagical, unattended object weighing up to 5 lb.</target>
                <duration>Concentration</duration>
                <save>None</save>
                <sr>No</sr>
                <text>You point your finger at an object and can lift it and move it at will from a distance. As a move
                    action, you can propel the object as far as 15 feet in any direction, though the spell ends if the
                    distance between you and the object ever exceeds the spell’s range.
                </text>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Bard</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Sorcerer</name>
                </spellClass>
                <spellClass>
                    <name>Wizard</name>
                </spellClass>
            </spell>
        </class>
        <class>
            <name>Enlightened Fist</name>
            <reflex>2</reflex>
            <will>2</will>
            <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            <slotsCurrent>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slotsCurrent>
            <modifier>
                <type>19</type>
                <value>10</value>
            </modifier>
            <autolevel>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>2</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>3</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>4</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>5</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>6</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>7</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>8</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>9</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>10</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>11</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>12</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>13</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>14</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>15</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>16</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>17</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>18</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>19</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
            <autolevel>
                <level>20</level>
                <slots>0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,</slots>
            </autolevel>
        </class>
        <skill>
            <name>Appraise</name>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>1</skillID>
            <name>Balance</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>2</skillID>
            <name>Bluff</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>3</skillID>
            <name>Climb</name>
            <ability>1</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>4</skillID>
            <name>Concentration</name>
            <ability>3</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>7</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>5</skillID>
            <name>Craft</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>6</skillID>
            <name>Decipher Script</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>7</skillID>
            <name>Diplomacy</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>8</skillID>
            <name>Disable Device</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>9</skillID>
            <name>Disguise</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>10</skillID>
            <name>Escape Artist</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>6</rank>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>11</skillID>
            <name>Forgery</name>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>12</skillID>
            <name>Gather Information</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>13</skillID>
            <name>Handle Animal</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>14</skillID>
            <name>Heal</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>15</skillID>
            <name>Hide</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>16</skillID>
            <name>Intimidate</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>17</skillID>
            <name>Jump</name>
            <ability>1</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>7</rank>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>18</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (arcana)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>5</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>19</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (architecture)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>20</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (dungeoneering)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>21</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (geography)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>22</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (history)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>23</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (local)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>24</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (nature)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>25</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (nobility)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>27</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (planes)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>26</skillID>
            <name>Knowledge (religion)</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>28</skillID>
            <name>Listen</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>8</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>29</skillID>
            <name>Move Silently</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>30</skillID>
            <name>Open Lock</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>31</skillID>
            <name>Perform</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>32</skillID>
            <name>Profession</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>33</skillID>
            <name>Ride</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <rank>1</rank>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>34</skillID>
            <name>Search</name>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>35</skillID>
            <name>Sense Motive</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>5</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>36</skillID>
            <name>Sleight of Hand</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>37</skillID>
            <name>Speak Language</name>
            <rank>1</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>38</skillID>
            <name>Spellcraft</name>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>5</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>39</skillID>
            <name>Spot</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>8</rank>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>40</skillID>
            <name>Survival</name>
            <ability>5</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>41</skillID>
            <name>Swim</name>
            <ability>1</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>1</rank>
            <armorPenalty>2</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>42</skillID>
            <name>Tumble</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
            <classSkill>1</classSkill>
            <rank>8</rank>
            <armorPenalty>1</armorPenalty>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>43</skillID>
            <name>Use Magic Device</name>
            <ability>6</ability>
        </skill>
        <skill>
            <skillID>44</skillID>
            <name>Use Rope</name>
            <ability>2</ability>
        </skill>
        <xp>49522</xp>
        <abilities>10,14,18,12,12,18,11,</abilities>
        <hpMax>64</hpMax>
        <hpCurrent>64</hpCurrent>
        <feat>
            <name>Weapon Finesse</name>
            <text>With a light weapon, rapier, whip, or spiked chain made for a creature of your size category, you may
                use your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength modifier on attack rolls. If you carry a shield,
                its armor check penalty applies to your attack rolls.
            </text>
            <special>3</special>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Improved Disarm</name>
            <text>You do not provoke an attack of opportunity when you attempt to disarm an opponent, nor does the
                opponent have a chance to disarm you. You also gain a +4 bonus on the opposed attack roll you make to
                disarm your opponent.
                Normal: See the normal disarm rules.
            </text>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Combat Reflexes</name>
            <text>You may make a number of additional attacks of opportunity equal to your Dexterity bonus.
                With this feat, you may also make attacks of opportunity while flat-footed.
                Normal: A character without this feat can make only one attack of opportunity per round and can’t make
                attacks of opportunity while flat-footed.
            </text>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Improved Initiative</name>
            <text>You get a +4 bonus on initiative checks.</text>
            <modifier></modifier>
            <modifier>
                <type>20</type>
                <value>4</value>
            </modifier>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Stunning Fist</name>
            <text>You must declare that you are using this feat before you make your attack roll (thus, a failed attack
                roll ruins the attempt). Stunning Fist forces a foe damaged by your unarmed attack to make a Fortitude
                saving throw (DC 10 + 1/2 your character level + your Wis modifier), in addition to dealing damage
                normally. A defender who fails this saving throw is stunned for 1 round (until just before your next
                action). A stunned character can’t act, loses any Dexterity bonus to AC, and takes a –2 penalty to AC.
                You may attempt a stunning attack once per day for every four levels you have attained (but see
                Special), and no more than once per round. Constructs, oozes, plants, undead, incorporeal creatures, and
                creatures immune to critical hits cannot be stunned.
            </text>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Practiced Spell caster</name>
            <text>Caster level +4</text>
        </feat>
        <feat>
            <name>Combat Casting</name>
            <text>You get a +4 bonus on Concentration checks made to cast a spell or use a spell-like ability while on
                the defensive or while you are grappling or pinned.
            </text>
        </feat>
        <action>
            <name>Unarmed</name>
            <attack>%8+%2+1</attack>
            <damage>1d10+3</damage>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Flury Of Misses</name>
            <attack>%8+%2</attack>
            <attack>%8+%2</attack>
            <attack>%8+%2-5</attack>
            <damage>1d10+3</damage>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Spiked Chain Disarm</name>
            <attack>%8+%2+1+4+4+2</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Sai</name>
            <attack>%8+%2</attack>
            <damage>1d4+%1-1</damage>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Kama</name>
            <attack>%8+%2-1</attack>
            <damage>1d6+%1-1</damage>
        </action>
        <item>
            <name>Necklace Of Natural Attacks +1</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
        </item>
        <item>
            <name>Ring Of Protection +1</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
            <modifier>
                <type>14</type>
                <value>6</value>
            </modifier>
        </item>
        <item>
            <name>Gloves Of Dexterity +2</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <type>15</type>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
            <modifier>
                <category>1</category>
                <type>1</type>
                <value>2</value>
            </modifier>
        </item>
        <item>
            <name>Bracers Of Armor +2</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
            <modifier>
                <type>9</type>
                <value>2</value>
            </modifier>
        </item>
        <item>
            <name>Ring of Jumping</name>
            <slot>1</slot>
            <damage>1d4</damage>
            <modifier>
                <category>2</category>
                <type>17</type>
                <value>5</value>
            </modifier>
        </item>
        <container>
            <name>Backpack</name>
            <item>
                <name>Wooden Stake</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Holy Symbol, Silver (Flargh)</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <value>1.0</value>
                <text>A holy symbol focuses positive energy. A cleric or paladin uses it as the focus for his spells and
                    as a tool for turning undead. Each religion has its own holy symbol.
                    Unholy Symbols: An unholy symbol is like a holy symbol except that it focuses negative energy and is
                    used by evil clerics (or by neutral clerics who want to cast evil spells or command undead).
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Brooch</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <value>600.0</value>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Chalk</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <value>0.01</value>
                <quantity>3</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Bedroll</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>5.0</weight>
                <value>0.1</value>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Potion Bandolier</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Rations, Trail (per day)</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>1.0</weight>
                <value>0.5</value>
                <quantity>5</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Explorer’s Outfit</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <weight>8.0</weight>
                <value>10.0</value>
                <text>This is a full set of clothes for someone who never knows what to expect. It includes sturdy
                    boots, leather breeches or a skirt, a belt, a shirt (perhaps with a vest or jacket), gloves, and a
                    cloak. Rather than a leather skirt, a leather overtunic may be worn over a cloth skirt. The clothes
                    have plenty of pockets (especially the cloak). The outfit also includes any extra items you might
                    need, such as a scarf or a wide-brimmed hat.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Gold</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <value>1060.0</value>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Garlic Necklace</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Holy Water</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Enlarge Scroll</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
        </container>
        <container>
            <name>Weapons</name>
            <item>
                <name>Chain, Spiked (Masterwork)</name>
                <type>6</type>
                <damage>2d4</damage>
                <damageType>2</damageType>
                <property>1154</property>
                <weight>10.0</weight>
                <value>25.0</value>
                <text>A spiked chain has reach, so you can strike opponents 10 feet away with it. In addition, unlike
                    most other weapons with reach, it can be used against an adjacent foe.
                    You can make trip attacks with the chain. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can
                    drop the chain to avoid being tripped.
                    When using a spiked chain, you get a +2 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an opponent
                    (including the roll to avoid being disarmed if such an attempt fails).
                    You can use the Weapon Finesse feat to apply your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength
                    modifier to attack rolls with a spiked chain sized for you, even though it isn’t a light weapon for
                    you.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Sai (Silver)</name>
                <type>4</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <damageType>1</damageType>
                <range>10</range>
                <property>2</property>
                <weight>1.0</weight>
                <value>1.0</value>
                <text>With a sai, you get a +4 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an enemy (including the roll
                    to avoid being disarmed if such an attempt fails).
                    The sai is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a sai special options.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Sai (Cold Iron)</name>
                <type>4</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <damageType>1</damageType>
                <range>10</range>
                <property>2</property>
                <weight>1.0</weight>
                <value>1.0</value>
                <text>With a sai, you get a +4 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an enemy (including the roll
                    to avoid being disarmed if such an attempt fails).
                    The sai is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a sai special options.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Sling &#38; Bullets (Cold Iron)</name>
                <type>7</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <damageType>1</damageType>
                <range>50</range>
                <property>2048</property>
                <quantity>20</quantity>
                <text>Your Strength modifier applies to damage rolls when you use a sling, just as it does for thrown
                    weapons. You can fire, but not load, a sling with one hand. Loading a sling is a move action that
                    requires two hands and provokes attacks of opportunity.
                    You can hurl ordinary stones with a sling, but stones are not as dense or as round as bullets. Thus,
                    such an attack deals damage as if the weapon were designed for a creature one size category smaller
                    than you and you take a –1 penalty on attack rolls.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Nunchaku</name>
                <type>4</type>
                <damage>1d6</damage>
                <damageType>1</damageType>
                <property>2</property>
                <weight>2.0</weight>
                <value>2.0</value>
                <text>The nunchaku is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a nunchaku special
                    options. With a nunchaku, you get a +2 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an enemy
                    (including the roll to avoid being disarmed if such an attempt fails).
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Shuriken Cold Iron</name>
                <type>7</type>
                <damage>1d2</damage>
                <damageType>2</damageType>
                <range>10</range>
                <property>2</property>
                <weight>0.5</weight>
                <value>1.0</value>
                <text>A shuriken is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding shuriken special
                    options. A shuriken can’t be used as a melee weapon.
                    Although they are thrown weapons, shuriken are treated as ammunition for the purposes of drawing
                    them, crafting masterwork or otherwise special versions of them and what happens to them after they
                    are thrown.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Javelin</name>
                <type>7</type>
                <damage>1d6</damage>
                <damageType>1</damageType>
                <range>30</range>
                <weight>2.0</weight>
                <value>1.0</value>
                <quantity>2</quantity>
                <text>Since it is not designed for melee, you are treated as nonproficient with it and take a –4 penalty
                    on attack rolls if you use a javelin as a melee weapon.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Quarterstaff</name>
                <slot>3</slot>
                <type>6</type>
                <damage>1d6</damage>
                <damageType>1</damageType>
                <property>64</property>
                <weight>4.0</weight>
                <text>A quarterstaff is a double weapon. You can fight with it as if fighting with two weapons, but if
                    you do, you incur all the normal attack penalties associated with fighting with two weapons, just as
                    if you were using a one-handed weapon and a light weapon. A creature wielding a quarterstaff in one
                    hand can’t use it as a double weapon0only one end of the weapon can be used in any given round.
                    The quarterstaff is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a quarterstaff
                    special options.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Kama(Silver)</name>
                <type>4</type>
                <damage>1d6</damage>
                <damageType>3</damageType>
                <property>2</property>
                <weight>2.0</weight>
                <value>2.0</value>
                <text>The kama is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a kama special options.
                    You can use a kama to make trip attacks. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can
                    drop the kama to avoid being tripped.
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Kama +2</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
        </container>
        <container>
            <name>Saddle Bags</name>
        </container>
        <container>
            <name>Potions</name>
            <item>
                <name>Mage Armor</name>
                <type>9</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>5</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Alter Self</name>
                <type>9</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Cure Moderate</name>
                <type>9</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Spiderclimb</name>
                <type>9</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Cats Grace</name>
                <type>9</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Hide</name>
                <type>9</type>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Neutralize Poison</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Alchemist Fire</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
            </item>
        </container>
        <container>
            <name>Wands</name>
            <item>
                <name>Shield50</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>34</quantity>
            </item>
            <item>
                <name>Mage Armor</name>
                <damage>1d4</damage>
                <quantity>19</quantity>
            </item>
        </container>
        <note>
            <title>Languages</title>
            <text>Common, Draconic</text>
        </note>
        <monster>
            <name>Horse, Light</name>
            <size>5</size>
            <type>Animal</type>
            <initiative>1</initiative>
            <senses>low-light vision, scent</senses>
            <ac>13</ac>
            <flatFootedAC>12</flatFootedAC>
            <acMods>-1 size, +1 Dex, +3 natural</acMods>
            <hpMax>19</hpMax>
            <hpCurrent>19</hpCurrent>
            <hd>3d8+6</hd>
            <fortitude>5</fortitude>
            <reflex>4</reflex>
            <will>2</will>
            <speed>60 ft.</speed>
            <attackMelee>2 hooves -2 (1d4+1*)</attackMelee>
            <space>10 ft.</space>
            <reach>5 ft.</reach>
            <abilities>10,14,13,15,2,12,6,</abilities>
            <baseAttack>2</baseAttack>
            <grapple>8</grapple>
            <feats>Endurance, Run</feats>
            <skills>Listen +4, Spot +4</skills>
            <feat>
                <name>Carrying Capacity</name>
                <text>A light load for a light horse is up to 150 pounds; a medium load, 151-300 pounds; and a heavy
                    load, 301-450 pounds. A light horse can drag 2,250 pounds.
                </text>
            </feat>
            <action>
                <name>Hooves</name>
                <attack>-2</attack>
                <damage>1d4+1</damage>
            </action>
        </monster>
        <modifier>
            <type>9</type>
            <value>2</value>
        </modifier>
        <modifier>
            <type>13</type>
            <value>4</value>
            <activated>false</activated>
        </modifier>
        <modifier>
            <type>9</type>
            <value>4</value>
        </modifier>
        <modifier>
            <category>1</category>
            <value>2</value>
            <activated>false</activated>
        </modifier>
        <modifier>
            <category>1</category>
            <type>1</type>
            <value>-2</value>
            <activated>false</activated>
        </modifier>
    </character>
</pc>